<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd"
  xmlns:trackback="http://madskills.com/public/xml/rss/module/trackback/">
  <channel>
    <title>Romulus Crisan</title>
    <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com</link>
    <description>Romulus Crisan is a software developer, trainer, speaker, agile.</description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2015 13:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
    <item>
      <title>I'm a developer, why bother with translation industry?</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/05/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-developer-translation-industry.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[This is the second part of the OpenExchange: Age of Developers series and is meant to highlight a few benefits of getting involved in the translation industry as a developer.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/05/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-developer-translation-industry.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2015 13:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/05/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-developer-translation-industry.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/age-of-developers-developer-translation-industry/developer-translation-industry.jpg" alt="Age Of Developers" title="Age of Developers" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">This is the second part of the <a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html" target="_blank">OpenExchange: Age of Developers</a> series and is meant to highlight a few benefits of getting involved in the translation industry as a developer.</p>

<h3 id="age-of-developers---table-of-contents">Age of developers - table of contents</h3>

<p>As I release parts of this series I will update this page with links to the articles.</p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-translator-code.html">I’m a translator do I need to write code?</a></li>
  <li>I’m a developer, why bother with translation industry?</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="translation-industry">Translation industry</h3>

<p>I’m a developer, my heart beats 01010101…, so I’m not going to bore you with market shares, revenues and other big numbers about how big this industry is. If you are really curious about this have a look <a href="http://www.pangeanic.com/knowledge_center/size-of-the-translation-industry/#">here</a>. What I would like to say is how important this industry is in today’s world and to sustain my affirmation look at these numbers:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Only 27% of Internet users speak English</li>
  <li>70% of internet traffic comes from non-English native countries</li>
  <li>34% of Twitter messages are in English</li>
  <li>75% of Facebook users are outside of US</li>
</ul>

<p>Interesting numbers I must say and they clearly show how relevant this industry is. Now some of you might have heard about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Machine_translation">machine translation</a> but the translation industry is much more than that. It’s about language localization, interpretation and terminology. </p>

<h3 id="technology">Technology</h3>

<p>Now let’s get closer to what we as developers are interested in, which is the technology. Each industry has its own specific terminology so I would like to take this opportunity to briefly explain some of the terms:</p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="http://www.translationzone.com/products/cat-tools/">CAT tools (Computer-Assisted Translation)</a> - typically these are desktop applications that aid translators and linguists to increase their translation productivity. While these applications will continue to be predominant on the desktop, web solutions will slowly appear that will add new options for translators and linguists.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.translationzone.com/products/translation-memory/#tag1">Translation Memories</a> - this are databases that store segments, which can be sentences, paragraphs, headings, titles or elements, from any filetype, in a list that has been translated. CAT tools rely on translation memories to aid the translator during the translation.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.translationzone.com/products/terminology-management/#tag1">Termbase</a> - this is a central repository, like a database, which allows translators to systematically manage approved terms.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.translationzone.com/products/machine-translation/#tag1">Machine translation</a> - this is about automated translation of natural languages. Probably all of you have used <a href="http://www.freetranslation.com/">free translation</a> or <a href="https://translate.google.ro/">google translate</a> which are the great examples of machine translation at work. The examples I’ve given are just end-user products but each platform exposes machine translation capabilities through various api’s as part of a <a href="https://languagecloud.sdl.com/translation-toolkit/api-documentation">cloud offering</a>.</li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Postediting">Post-editing</a> - this is the process of improving a machine generated translation and typically is done from a CAT tool.  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="why-bother">Why bother?</h3>

<p>Now that I’ve given you a brief overview of the translation industry the big question is why should I, as a developer, bother getting into this. I already know desktop, web, mobile and/or cloud technologies and I also have to keep up with the fast pace of technology changes. That might be true but if you really want to be a great specialist it’s not enough just to know some technologies, you need to make them relevant. People expect solutions for their problems from developers and good solutions require industry expertise. If someone asks you to build them an accounting system you don’t need to be an expert accountant but you need to know a few things about accounting. I highly recommend reading the article from John Sonmez “<a href="http://simpleprogrammer.com/2015/04/23/im-not-sure-i-want-to-be-a-specialist/">I’m not sure I want to be a specialist</a>” which emphasizes on specializing as a developer.</p>

<p>Becoming a specialist will help you become a better professional, find interesting job opportunities or even become a freelance developer if this is something you’re looking for. </p>

<p>Specializing in a specific industry makes perfect sense and this why I consider that you as a developer should take into consideration the translation industry.</p>

<h3 id="where-do-i-start">Where do I start?</h3>

<p>A great way to learn about the translation industry is to start develop plugins and apps for existing products. The <a href="www.sdl.com/openexchange">SDL OpenExchange</a> app store is nice way to publish your work and maybe even earn some money. At the very best you will gain exposure as a developer to those translations companies looking for development expertise to help them integrate their own systems or gain some competitive advantage by asking you to implement some ideas of their own. To publish an app on SDL OpenExchange you need to become an SDL OpenExchange developer. This is a simple process you can follow from <a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/developer/">here</a>. You don’t need to worry about licenses since SDL can offer dedicated developer licenses:</p>

<ol>
  <li>CAT Tool - SDL’s CAT tool name is <a href="http://www.sdl.com/cxc/language/translation-productivity/trados-studio/">SDL Trados Studio 2015</a> and in order to develop anything on top if it you’ll need a license. In order to get a developer license please create an SDL OpenExchange developer account and then send an email to app-signing@sdl.com and this will be sorted out</li>
  <li>Machine Translation - SDL’s machine translation cloud solution is named <a href="https://languagecloud.sdl.com/">Language Cloud</a> and you can sign-up for a developer account <a href="https://languagecloud.sdl.com/translation-toolkit/sign-up">here</a>.  </li>
</ol>

<p>Every new journey might be a bit bumpy in the beginning and you should not hesitate to ask for help. I recommend to register in the <a href="https://community.sdl.com/developers/language-developers/">language developer community</a> and ask for help there. </p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>My best advice is to have patience, practice as much as possible and don’t be afraid to ask. I’m sure the results will come sooner or later. Happy coding. </p>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-08-05T13:00:00+03:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I'm a translator do I need to write code?</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-translator-code.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[This is the first part of the OpenExchange: Age of Developers series. This article is meant to be a short guide for translators who are willing to augment their productivity and ease their day to day work by writing plugins for Sdl Studio, but they don't know from where to start.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-translator-code.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2015 13:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-translator-code.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/age-of-developers-translator-code/age-of-developers-translator-code.jpg" alt="Age Of Developers" title="Age of Developers" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">This is the first part of the <a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html" target="_blank">OpenExchange: Age of Developers</a> series. This article is meant to be a short guide for translators who are willing to augment their productivity and ease their day to day work by writing plugins for SDL Studio, but they don't know from where to start.</p>

<h3 id="age-of-developers---table-of-contents">Age of developers - table of contents</h3>

<p>As I release parts of this series I will update this page with links to the articles.</p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html">Introduction</a></li>
  <li>I’m a translator do I need to write code?</li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/05/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-developer-translation-industry.html">I’m a developer, why bother with translation industry?</a></li>
</ol>

<h3 id="im-a-translator-do-i-need-to-write-code">I’m a translator do I need to write code?</h3>

<p>The short answer is yes. In order to make an SDL Studio plugin and publish it on the SDL OpenExchange you need to write code. SDL Studio is developed using Microsoft technology called <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/net">Microsoft .Net</a>. The platform allows you to build all kind of apps from desktop (like Studio) to web and mobile. <a href="http://www.hanselman.com/">Scott Hanselman</a>, principal program manager and community architect at Microsoft, estimates that there are <a href="http://www.quora.com/How-many-NET-developers-are-there">~8 million</a> .net developers out there. The <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/net">Microsoft .Net</a> platform has support for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_CLI_languages">many programming languages</a> but the most popular is C# (CSharp). I would recommend learning this language because you will be able to find many resources to help you in your learning journey.</p>

<h3 id="why-should-i-bother">Why should I bother?</h3>

<p>This is a tough one to answer since every person is different and there is no silver bullet answer. Something that resonates with one person might not resonate for someone else. So here’s my list of reasons that might help you answer this question:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Are you waiting for a feature to be added in the software? Take the responsibility into your own hands and fix it. You will feel accomplished after you’ve done it, you will gain recognition in the industry and why not even see if you can earn some extra money with it.</li>
  <li><a href="http://simpleprogrammer.com/2013/03/31/everyone-should-learn-to-program-but-not-everyone-should-be-a-programmer/">Everyone Should Learn To Program, But Not Everyone Should Be A Programmer</a> What if only writers could write and when you needed to write an email to your boss you had to ask the company writer do it? I agree that programming and writing are not the same thing but what I’m trying to say is that learning to program doesn’t necessarily mean you became a professional developer. There’s much more than just writing code to being a professional developer.</li>
  <li>Nowadays learning to write code is much easier than it was 5, 10 or 20 years ago. You have much better tooling and the languages are much more abstract, meaning you don’t need to know all the details of how the computer works in order to write a line of code.</li>
  <li>There is a strong movement for every child to learn how to program. This doesn’t mean everyone should become a developer but it’s the best way to promote <a href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/link/research-notebook-computational-thinking-what-and-why">computational thinking</a>. Computational thinking teaches you how to tackle large problems by breaking them down into smaller, more manageable problems.</li>
</ul>

<p>I hope this will help you understand why should you bother to learn to program (or write code).</p>

<h3 id="where-do-i-start">Where do I start?</h3>

<p>The first thing you need to start writing apps for the SDL OpenExchange is Microsoft Visual Studio. This is the tool of choice when writing code for the <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/net">Microsoft .Net</a> platform. The good news is that you can get a free version with all the features you need. This version is called the Visual Studio Community Edition and can be downloaded from <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/products/visual-studio-community-vs.aspx">here</a>. You can select the 2015 or 2013 version, both of them are suitable for creating SDL OpenExchange plugins. 2015 has only just been released and contains lots of new features for experienced developers.</p>

<p>The next step would be to start learning some basics of programming in C#. There are books you can read, but personally I like watching videos so here’s some courses you could look into:</p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="https://www.microsoftvirtualacademy.com/en-US/training-courses/c-fundamentals-for-absolute-beginners-8295">C# Fundamentals for Absolute Beginners</a> This will walk you through all the code examples you need to build basic applications using C#. At the time this video was recorded the Visual Studio Community Edition had not been released so this is not mentioned but I recommend you to use it instead of the Visual Studio Express Edition.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.microsoftvirtualacademy.com/en-US/training-courses/software-development-fundamentals-8248">Software Development Fundamentals</a> This is a very detailed presentation on software development in general not necessarily only with C#. Some of the parts might be a bit advanced and are not essential if the main objective here is to learn some basic programming rather than becoming a programmer.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.pluralsight.com/courses/csharp-fundamentals-csharp5">C# Fundamentals with C# 5.0</a> This is a great video which I highly recommend but it’s different to the first two in my list because you have to pay for this service. You do get over 4000 courses of great quality though!</li>
</ol>

<p>Although watching those videos provides lots of information the best way to really learn is by practice, so I highly suggest you stop the videos and practice what you’ve seen at every opportunity. </p>

<p>If you prefer to learn from books I highly recommend <a href="http://csharpindepth.com/">C# in depth</a> but I would still suggest you supplement the book with some of the above videos.</p>

<p>One last thing, you’re not alone in this so don’t hesitate to ask for help. As I’ve said earlier in the article, there’s a really big .net community. My suggestions would be to ask any questions on the <a href="https://community.sdl.com/developers/language-developers/">SDL Language Developers</a> community website. Don’t hesitate to ask general programming questions in there even if they are not directly related to any of SDL products. There is the <a href="https://community.sdl.com/developers/language-developers/f/61">Getting Started</a> area which is just the right place for this type of discussion.</p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>My best advice is to have patience, practice as much as possible and don’t be afraid to ask. I’m sure the results will come sooner or later. Happy coding. </p>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-07-20T13:00:00+03:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenExchange: Age of developers</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[OpenExchange was launched a few years back by SDL with the purpose to allow anyone to integrate their solutions or ideas with the SDL Language Platform. This gave everyone freedom to augment the SDL platform according to their needs. Because of this freedom, apps like Glossary Converter, MSWord Grammar Checker and many others where possible. It's pretty obvious that this brings great value to every SDL language platform user, but how about building those apps? From where should I start? I'm a translator do I need to program? I have no idea about the translation industry, what can I do?]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2015 13:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/age-of-developers-intro/age-of-developers-intro.jpg" alt="Age Of Developers" title="Age of Developers" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">OpenExchange was launched a few years back by SDL with the purpose to allow anyone to integrate their solutions or ideas with the SDL language platform. This gave everyone freedom to augment the SDL language platform according to their needs. Because of this freedom, apps like <a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/app/glossaryconverter-476.html#46146" target="_blank">Glossary Converter</a>, <a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/app/mswordgrammarcheckerforstudio2015-796.html#85390">MSWord Grammar Checker</a> and many others where possible. It's pretty obvious that this brings great value to every SDL language platform user, but how about building those apps? From where should I start? I'm a translator do I need to write code? I have no idea about the translation industry, what can I do? </p>

<h3 id="age-of-developers">Age of developers</h3>

<p>This is the introduction article for a series of blog posts that I’m about to write about how you can develop apps or plugins for OpenExchange throughout which I will answer the above questions and many others. If you’re not a developer but you would like to be able to build something don’t worry I will show you how you can start learn programming, if you are a developer already but don’t have a clue about translation industry and what can you do I got you covered as well. I will start from ground zero providing step by step explanation on how you need to setup the development environment, what tools you need and from where you can get them. Throughout the series I will develop a plugin and share with you the steps I’m doing and also the source code.</p>

<p>As I release parts of this series I will update this page with links to the articles.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Introduction</li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-translator-code.html">I’m a translator do I need to write code?</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/05/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-developer-translation-industry.html">I’m a developer, why bother with translation industry?</a></li>
</ol>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-07-20T13:00:00+03:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integration API enhancements introduced in SDL Studio CU10</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/06/02/Integration%20API%20enhancements%20introduced%20in%20SDL%20Studio%20CU10.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[Latest SDL Studio update, cumulative update 10, was released on 13th of May and together with this update there a few additions to the integration API. If you want to see the entire list of changes included in this update have a look at the sdl knowledge base. Now lets get down to business and talk about the integration api changes.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/06/02/Integration%20API%20enhancements%20introduced%20in%20SDL%20Studio%20CU10.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2015 22:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/06/02/Integration%20API%20enhancements%20introduced%20in%20SDL%20Studio%20CU10.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/integration-api-enhancements-cu10/integration-api-enhancements-cu10.jpg" alt="Integration API enhancements introduce in SDL Studio CU10" title="Integration API enhancements introduce in SDL Studio CU10" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">Latest SDL Studio update, cumulative update 10, was released on 13th of May and together with this update there a few additions to the integration API. If you want to see the entire list of changes included in this update have a look <a href="http://kb.sdl.com/#tab:homeTab:crumb:7:artId:5375" target="_blank">here</a>. Now lets get down to business and talk about the integration api changes.</p>

<h3 id="table-of-contents">Table of contents</h3>

<p>This is a pretty long post and you might not want to read through the entire article so if you want to read only a specific topic I prepared a jump-list with the topics I cover in this article:</p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="#segment-translation-on-demand">Segment translation on-demand</a></li>
  <li><a href="#active-file-properties">Active file properties</a></li>
  <li><a href="#accessupdate-segment-and-paragraph-unit-properties">Access/update segment and paragraph unit properties</a></li>
  <li><a href="#crud-operations-on-comments">CRUD operations on comments</a></li>
  <li><a href="#change-segment-confirmation-level">Change segment confirmation level</a></li>
  <li><a href="#autosuggest-provider-icon">AutoSuggest provider icon</a></li>
  <li><a href="#segment-content-ready">Segment Content ready</a></li>
</ol>

<h3 id="segment-translation-on-demand">Segment translation on-demand</h3>

<p>Segment translation is done by the translation providers that are configured and enabled at the project level. This can happen as a pre-translation step or when the current segment is changed by the user in the user interface. With this new feature added to the integration API a developer is able to request the translation of the current selected segment whenever this is needed. This can be done from the <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/StudioIntegrationApi/3.0/html/2a868ca0-831d-4614-9763-2bf928a0f3fb.htm">EditorController</a>. To see this in action you can look at this sample:</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/4676c94c596aa174c4f4.js"></script>

<p>This sample code is take from the <a href="https://github.com/sdl/Sdl-Community/tree/master/Controlled%20Machine%20Translation%20Providers">Controlled Machine Translation Providers</a> plugin.</p>

<h3 id="active-file-properties">Active file properties</h3>

<p>Until now developers were only able to get information about <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/ProjectAutomationApi/3.0/html/2b0cadd0-8be7-eea2-f974-bb14bdcb6db8.htm">ActiveFile</a> like statistics, language, project id and so on. There was no way to get information like creation date, change date, metada and so on. This is now possible using <em>ActiveFileProperties</em> property of the <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/StudioIntegrationApi/3.0/html/9bb61319-d033-7198-9aee-b29eb5f759e9.htm">Document</a> class. Also an event was added to notify when the active file properties are changed.</p>

<h3 id="accessupdate-segment-and-paragraph-unit-properties">Access/update segment and paragraph unit properties</h3>

<p>If you needed to make any work around segments the only available option was to use <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/StudioIntegrationApi/3.0/html/b4f43e30-8ba6-f2c2-7ea2-883ab83d1d67.htm">ProcessSegmentPairs</a> method from the <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/StudioIntegrationApi/3.0/html/9bb61319-d033-7198-9aee-b29eb5f759e9.htm">Document</a> class. Now this can do the trick but it’s not straightforward to use and can be an overhead for simple scenarios, also this method was not providing any way to interact with paragraph units. We’ve now added a couple other options that provide more granularity and flexibility in how a developer is able to process segments. We also added  capabilities to work directly with paragraph units. Here’s the list with the methods available:</p>

<ol>
  <li><em>GetSegmentPairsFromParagraph</em> - Based on the paragraph id you can obtain the segment pairs of that paragraph</li>
</ol>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/92f94e278fe1c41d6a46.js"></script>

<ol>
  <li><em>UpdateSegmentPair</em> - updates the document with the specified segment pair</li>
</ol>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/4182815a61117b5a3dbb.js"></script>

<ol>
  <li><em>UpdateSegmentPairProperties</em> - updates the document with the specified segment pair properties</li>
</ol>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/233216998995c82eaaef.js"></script>

<ol>
  <li><em>UpdateParagraphProperties</em> - updates the document with the specified paragraph properties</li>
</ol>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/c755798e710a09b153aa.js"></script>

<h3 id="crud-operations-on-comments">CRUD operations on comments</h3>

<p>Adding comments was only possible using <a href="https://community.sdl.com/developers/language-developers/f/57/p/3414/12658#12658">Billingual API</a>. While this is fine when you want to do it for your custom file type is not productive to use it when you just want to add comments to your well known file type. To solve this issue the integration api has now specialized methods that allow <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Create,_read,_update_and_delete">CRUD</a> operations for comments. Here’s the list with the methods available: </p>

<ol>
  <li><em>AddCommentOnSegment</em></li>
</ol>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/86234330eb378a3798de.js"></script>

<ol>
  <li><em>UpdateCommentOnSegment</em></li>
</ol>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/5b1931864dcbe16935e1.js"></script>

<ol>
  <li><em>DeleteCommentOnSegment</em></li>
</ol>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/a281d232959dbabe1222.js"></script>

<ol>
  <li><em>DeleteAllCommentsOnSegment</em></li>
</ol>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/363b895641c7443c1bdf.js"></script>

<h3 id="change-segment-confirmation-level">Change segment confirmation level</h3>

<p>Developers are now able to change the segment confirmation level using the integration API and also they can now subscribe to an event that is trigger when the confirmation level is changed.</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/b70a13dd8c08f8882ecb.js"></script>

<h3 id="autosuggest-provider-icon">AutoSuggest provider icon</h3>

<p>Developer can now add custom icons for their AutoSuggest providers.</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/a55d2a6b9cbd848af1b7.js"></script>

<h3 id="segment-content-ready">Segment Content ready</h3>

<p>There are situations where you may want to do some additional work after the translation has been done. To cover this type of situation the event <em>ActiveSegmentContentIsReady</em> was added to the <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/StudioIntegrationApi/3.0/html/9bb61319-d033-7198-9aee-b29eb5f759e9.htm">Document</a> class.</p>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-06-02T22:00:00+03:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Playing with SDL Studio settings</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/05/27/Playing%20with%20SDL%20Studio%20settings.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[SDL Studio is a complex and extendable application witch comes with a few APIs that allows any developer to extend the application in all kind of ways. To be more exact there are 6 APIs you can use to build your application. This degree of complexity and extensibility translates in a huge amount of settings you can play with. The user interface does a great job present them in a meaningful way but that is not the same when you want to develop something in your custom applications and you need to read or update some of the settings.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/05/27/Playing%20with%20SDL%20Studio%20settings.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2015 22:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/05/27/Playing%20with%20SDL%20Studio%20settings.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/playing-with-settings/playing-with-settings.png" alt="Playing with SDL Studio settings" title="Playing with SDL Studio settings" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">SDL Studio is a complex and extendable application witch comes with a few APIs that allows any developer to extend the application in all kind of ways. To be more exact there are 6 APIs you can use to build your application. This degree of complexity and extensibility translates in a huge amount of settings you can play with. The user interface does a great job presenting them in a meaningful way but that is not the same when you want to develop something in your custom applications and you need to read or update some of the settings.</p>

<h3 id="project-settings">Project Settings</h3>

<p>Lets say you are in a situation where the API is not offering you direct access to the user setting you would like to change, what options you have in this situation? A great amount of settings are store in the project file which in essence it’s an xml file. This mean I could use the standard .NET libraries to parse the project xml file and change what I need. This is completely true and can be done but the problem is knowing the xml structure which for the project file can be pretty complex and hard to understand. To give you an example the project file for a very simple test project is over 1000 lines. Understanding those lines can take some time and patience. Before continuing I want to clarify one thing which is knowing that the SDL Studio project file is not only about user settings it’s much more than that, things that are used internal by Studio so we need to be very careful when we change anything in this file. My recommendation would be to use the <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/Core/3.0/search.html?SearchText=settingsbundle">settings classes</a> exposed by SDL Studio Core API.</p>

<h3 id="settings-bundle-and-group">Settings Bundle and Group</h3>

<p>User settings are stored in hierarchical structure as settings bundles. A bundle is bound to a feature from SDL Studio. For example I can have a settings bundle for project specific settings, another project bundle with settings for language direction, another one for language file and so on. Each bundle will have unique identifier as a GUID value and can have one or multiple child elements in form of settings group. A settings group represent a smaller piece from the bundle feature and can have, as child’s, one or multiple settings. As an example of settings group you can think at specific settings for a file type which is part of the project settings bundle.</p>

<p>With this said the SDL Studio API has <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/Core/3.0/html/9e4ba18c-dab1-bb47-0ce7-a31fb3002ba3.htm">ISettingsBundle</a> interface and a <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/Core/3.0/html/72c76110-8d6c-6315-58d9-dc36b998d14b.htm">SettingsGroup</a> class used to represent the hierarchical structure I explained above. The API doesn’t expose a concrete implementation of <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/Core/3.0/html/9e4ba18c-dab1-bb47-0ce7-a31fb3002ba3.htm">ISettingsBundle</a> so you need to use <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/Core/3.0/html/ae69c32c-3ebe-946f-3e3c-d091278a407f.htm">SettingsUtils</a> class to create an instance of settings bundle.</p>

<h3 id="real-use-case">Real use case</h3>

<p>To clarify the things a bit I want to show you a real use case where you can use the settings classes from the SDL Studio Core API. Let’s say that for a project we want to disable all the global verifiers. This value is kept in the project file and can be changed using .NET xml libraries or using the settings classes I explained in the previous paragraph. Here’s the code required to implement this feature:</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/7299796351f364d93aa5.js"></script>

<p>In this case I obtain the settings group id by instantiating all the global verifiers but you can request the setting group also by just providing the string. </p>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-05-27T22:00:00+03:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Studio plugin versioning</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/05/05/Studio%20plugin%20versioning.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[SDL Studio 2015 is just around the corner and as a plugin developer there are a few things you should do to make your plugin compatible with this new Studio version. Now with all Studio versions out there some may ask how can I control my plugin versions and how can I make sure my plugin will be used only by the appropriate version of SDL Studio.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/05/05/Studio%20plugin%20versioning.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2015 22:20:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/05/05/Studio%20plugin%20versioning.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/studio-plugin-versioning/version.jpg" alt="Studio plugin versioning" title="Studio plugin versioning" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">SDL Studio 2015 is just around the corner and as a plugin developer there are a few things you should do to make your plugin compatible with this new Studio version. You can read more about this here: <a href="https://community.sdl.com/developers/language-developers/w/wiki/647.steps-to-upgrade-your-plugin-for-studio-2015">Steps to upgrade your plugin for Studio 2015</a>. Now with all Studio versions out there some may ask how can I control my plugin versions and how can I make sure my plugin will be used only by the appropriate version of SDL Studio.</p>

<h3 id="plugin-manifest">Plugin manifest</h3>

<p>Every plugin must contain a manifest file that defines a few general information about your plugin. The file is called <em>pluginpackage.manifest.xml</em> and if you open any *.sdlplugin file with and archiving tool, like <a href="http://www.7-zip.org/">7zip</a>, you should be able to see it and open it. Also when you create a new plugin solution in Microsoft Visual Studio this file will be automatically created for you and it will be included in our plugin package (.sdlplugin file). In this file you can add your plugin name, description, author, version, required product and you can <a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2014/11/07/3rd-party-assmeblies-and-SDL-Studio-plugins.html">specify additional files to be included in the package</a>.</p>

<h3 id="plugin-versioning">Plugin versioning</h3>

<p>As I highlighted before you can specify a plugin version by using the tag:
&gt; Version</p>

<p>This is used by SDL Studio to remove previously deployed plugins. For example if you have on your machine a plugin with version 0.1.0.0 if you install a new version like 0.1.1.0 it will automatically remove the unpacked version of the plugin and unpack the newer version. If the version is the same or lower this will not happen hence you will have to do it yourself.</p>

<h3 id="product-versioning">Product versioning</h3>

<p>Besides plugin versioning you can also specify SDL Studio versions that are compatible with your plugin. This can be done using the tag:
&gt;RequiredProduct</p>

<p>On this tag you can specify in the attribute <em>minversion</em> the lowest SDL Studio version that is compatible with your plugin. For example if you specify a minimum version of <em>10.0</em> this means that your plugin will be compatible with Studio 2011 or higher. If you want to limit your plugin just to a specific SDL Studio version you can also specify a <em>maxversion</em> attribute. So for example if in our case we add a maximum version of <em>10.9</em> this will not be compatible with Studio 2014 or higher and even if it’s copied into the Studio 2014 plugins folder it will be ignored.</p>

<h3 id="universal-plugin-installer">Universal plugin installer</h3>

<p>The universal plugin installer is also using this information to avoid deploying plugins that are not compatible with a specific Studio version. If you are not familiar with the universal plugin installer you can read more here: <a href="https://github.com/sdl/Sdl-plugin-installer">SDL plugin installer</a>.</p>

<h3 id="final-words">Final words</h3>

<p>I recommend to review your manifest file and take advantage of the versioning capabilities. Even if there is no obvious reason at the moment it might prove handy in the future. </p>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-05-05T22:20:00+03:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code by the book</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/career/2015/04/19/Code-by-the-book.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[A few weeks back a friend of mine asked me to recommend him some programming/technical books. I was busy at that moment so I couldn't write my recommendations but he suggested that I should write an article on my blog. I thought that it's a great idea so here it is my list of recommendations. Although most of the times a I code in C# most of the books are technology agnostic which means every developer can read them.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/career/2015/04/19/Code-by-the-book.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2015 22:20:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/career/2015/04/19/Code-by-the-book.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/code-by-the-book/books.jpg" alt="Code by the book" title="Code by the book" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">A few weeks back a friend of mine asked me to recommend him some programming/technical books. I was busy at that moment so I couldn't write my recommendations but he suggested that I should write an article on my blog. I thought that it's a great idea so here it is my list of recommendations. Although most of the times a I code in C# most of the books are technology agnostic which means every developer can read them.</p>

<h3 id="for-blooming-developers">For blooming developers</h3>

<p>This are some of the books I recommend for developers which are just starting their career. It’s not that they shouldn’t read more advanced books but those might be a bit too difficult for the moment.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Clean-Code-Handbook-Software-Craftsmanship/dp/0132350882">Clean Code: A Handbook of Agile Software Craftsmanship</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Robert-C.-Martin/e/B000APG87E/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Robert C. Martin</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The book is divided into three parts. The first describes the principles, patterns, and practices of writing clean code. The second part consists of several case studies of increasing complexity. Each case study is an exercise in cleaning up code—of transforming a code base that has some problems into one that is sound and efficient. The third part is the payoff: a single chapter containing a list of heuristics and “smells” gathered while creating the case studies. The result is a knowledge base that describes the way we think when we write, read, and clean code. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Clean-Code-Handbook-Software-Craftsmanship/dp/0132350882">Amazon</a> </p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Clean-Coder-Professional-Programmers/dp/0137081073">The Clean Coder: A Code of Conduct for Professional Programmers</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Robert-C.-Martin/e/B000APG87E/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Robert C. Martin</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In The Clean Coder: A Code of Conduct for Professional Programmers, legendary software expert Robert C. Martin introduces the disciplines, techniques, tools, and practices of true software craftsmanship. This book is packed with practical advice–about everything from estimating and coding to refactoring and testing. It covers much more than technique: It is about attitude. Martin shows how to approach software development with honor, self-respect, and pride; work well and work clean; communicate and estimate faithfully; face difficult decisions with clarity and honesty; and understand that deep knowledge comes with a responsibility to act. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Clean-Coder-Professional-Programmers/dp/0137081073">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Depth-3rd-Edition-Jon-Skeet/dp/161729134X">C# in Depth, 3rd Edition</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Jon-Skeet/e/B001JP0M8K/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Jon Skeet</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>C# in Depth is a book for those who are passionate about C#. It aims to be a bridge between the existing introductory books and the language specification: something readable but detailed, exploring every aspect of the language from version 2 onwards. In the interests of brevity, it doesn’t spend much time on C# 1 - readers are already expected to know the first version at least reasonably. Every new feature from C# 2 onwards is covered, however, as shown in the table of contents below. - <a href="http://csharpindepth.com/">C# in Depth</a></p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="for-experienced-developers">For experienced developers</h3>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Extreme-Programming-Explained-Embrace-Change/dp/0321278658/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475655&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=extreme+programming">Extreme Programming Explained: Embrace Change, 2nd Edition</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Kent-Beck/e/B000APC0EY/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Kent Beck</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Whether you have a small team that is already closely aligned with your customers or a large team in a gigantic or multinational organization, you will find in these pages a wealth of ideas to challenge, inspire, and encourage you and your team members to substantially improve your software development. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Extreme-Programming-Explained-Embrace-Change/dp/0321278658/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475655&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=extreme+programming">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Implementation-Patterns-Kent-Beck/dp/0321413091/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475615&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=implementation+patterns">Implementation Patterns</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Kent-Beck/e/B000APC0EY/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Kent Beck</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Implementation Patterns will help programmers at all experience levels, especially those who have benefited from software patterns or agile methods. It will also be an indispensable resource for development teams seeking to work together more efficiently and build more maintainable software. No other programming book will touch your day-to-day work more often. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Implementation-Patterns-Kent-Beck/dp/0321413091/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475615&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=implementation+patterns">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Domain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software/dp/0321125215/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475783&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=domain+driven+design">Domain-Driven Design: Tackling Complexity in the Heart of Software</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Eric-Evans/e/B001KDCO2I/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Eric Evans</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This book provides a broad framework for making design decisions and a technical vocabulary for discussing domain design. It is a synthesis of widely accepted best practices along with the author’s own insights and experiences. Projects facing complex domains can use this framework to approach domain-driven design systematically. - <a href="http://dddcommunity.org/book/evans_2003/">DDDCommunity</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Code-Complete-Practical-Handbook-Construction/dp/0735619670/ref=sr_1_sc_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475928&amp;sr=1-1-spell&amp;keywords=code+comoplete">Code Complete: A Practical Handbook of Software Construction, Second Edition</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Steve-McConnell/e/B000APETRK/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Steve McConnell</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Capturing the body of knowledge available from research, academia, and everyday commercial practice, McConnell synthesizes the most effective techniques and must-know principles into clear, pragmatic guidance. No matter what your experience level, development environment, or project size, this book will inform and stimulate your thinking—and help you build the highest quality code. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Code-Complete-Practical-Handbook-Construction/dp/0735619670/ref=sr_1_sc_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475928&amp;sr=1-1-spell&amp;keywords=code+comoplete">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Refactoring-Improving-Design-Existing-Code/dp/0201485672/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1429428810&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=refactoring+martin+fowler">Refactoring: Improving the Design of Existing Code</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Martin-Fowler/e/B000AQ6PGM/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Martin Fowler</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Kent-Beck/e/B000APC0EY/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_2">Kent Beck</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/s/ref=dp_byline_sr_book_3?ie=UTF8&amp;field-author=John+Brant&amp;search-alias=books&amp;text=John+Brant&amp;sort=relevancerank">John Brant</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/s/ref=dp_byline_sr_book_4?ie=UTF8&amp;field-author=William+Opdyke&amp;search-alias=books&amp;text=William+Opdyke&amp;sort=relevancerank">William Opdyke</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/s/ref=dp_byline_sr_book_5?ie=UTF8&amp;field-author=Don+Roberts&amp;search-alias=books&amp;text=Don+Roberts&amp;sort=relevancerank">Don Roberts</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Refactoring is about improving the design of existing code. It is the process of changing a software system in such a way that it does not alter the external behavior of the code, yet improves its internal structure. With refactoring you can even take a bad design and rework it into a good one. This book offers a thorough discussion of the principles of refactoring, including where to spot opportunities for refactoring, and how to set up the required tests. There is also a catalog of more than 40 proven refactorings with details as to when and why to use the refactoring, step by step instructions for implementing it, and an example illustrating how it works The book is written using Java as its principle language, but the ideas are applicable to any OO language. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Refactoring-Improving-Design-Existing-Code/dp/0201485672/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1429428810&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=refactoring+martin+fowler">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Continuous-Delivery-Deployment-Automation-Addison-Wesley/dp/0321601912/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475911&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=continuous+delivery">Continuous Delivery: Reliable Software Releases through Build, Test, and Deployment Automation</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Jez-Humble/e/B003SNGS8E/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Jez Humble</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/David-Farley/e/B003VSTZ72/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_2">David Farley</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Getting software released to users is often a painful, risky, and time-consuming process.
This groundbreaking new book sets out the principles and technical practices that enable
rapid, incremental delivery of high quality, valuable new functionality to users. Through
automation of the build, deployment, and testing process, and improved collaboration between
developers, testers, and operations, delivery teams can get changes released in a matter of hours—
sometimes even minutes–no matter what the size of a project or the complexity of its code base. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Continuous-Delivery-Deployment-Automation-Addison-Wesley/dp/0321601912/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475911&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=continuous+delivery">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Dependency-Injection-NET-Mark-Seemann/dp/1935182501/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475711&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=dependency+injection">Dependency Injection in .NET</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mark-Seemann/e/B004XYGMVK/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Mark Seemann</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Dependency Injection in .NET introduces DI and provides a practical guide for applying it in .NET applications. The book presents the core patterns in plain C#, so you’ll fully understand how DI works. Then you’ll learn to integrate DI with standard Microsoft technologies like ASP.NET MVC, and to use DI frameworks like StructureMap, Castle Windsor, and Unity. By the end of the book, you’ll be comfortable applying this powerful technique in your everyday .NET development. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Dependency-Injection-NET-Mark-Seemann/dp/1935182501/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475711&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=dependency+injection">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Art-Unit-Testing-examples/dp/1617290890/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475748&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=the+art+of+unit+testing">The Art of Unit Testing: with examples in C#</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Roy-Osherove/e/B00D3VXAG4/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Roy Osherove</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The Art of Unit Testing, Second Edition guides you step by step from writing your first simple unit tests to building complete test sets that are maintainable, readable, and trustworthy. You’ll move quickly to more complicated subjects like mocks and stubs, while learning to use isolation (mocking) frameworks like Moq, FakeItEasy, and Typemock Isolator. You’ll explore test patterns and organization, refactor code applications, and learn how to test “untestable” code. Along the way, you’ll learn about integration testing and techniques for testing with databases.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>The examples in the book use C#, but will benefit anyone using a statically typed language such as Java or C++. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Art-Unit-Testing-examples/dp/1617290890/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475748&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=the+art+of+unit+testing">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="for-those-about-to-rock">For those about to rock</h3>

<p>Software is about solving people problems and to do that you need more than just coding skills. If you want to rock you need to deliver the software as people expect it. On top of the technical books I recommend a few books that can help you rock.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/User-Stories-Applied-Software-Development/dp/0321205685">User Stories Applied: For Agile Software Development</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mike-Cohn/e/B001H6MN56/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Mike Cohn</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The best way to build software that meets users’ needs is to begin with “user stories”: simple, clear, brief descriptions of functionality that will be valuable to real users. In User Stories Applied, Mike Cohn provides you with a front-to-back blueprint for writing these user stories and weaving them into your development lifecycle. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/User-Stories-Applied-Software-Development/dp/0321205685">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Impact-Mapping-software-products-projects-ebook/dp/B009KWDKVA">Impact Mapping: Making a big impact with software products and projects</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Gojko-Adzic/e/B004P9W8G6/ref=ntt_athr_dp_pel_1">Gojko Adzic</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This handbook is a practical guide to impact mapping, a simple yet incredibly effective method for collaborative strategic planning that helps organisations make an impact with software. Impact mapping helps to create better plans and roadmaps that ensure alignment of business and delivery, and are easily adaptable to change. Impact mapping fits nicely into several current trends in software product management and release planning, including goal-oriented requirements engineering, frequent iterative delivery, agile and lean software methods, lean startup product development cycles, and design thinking. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Impact-Mapping-software-products-projects-ebook/dp/B009KWDKVA">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="https://leanpub.com/50quickideas">Fifty Quick Ideas to Improve your User Stories</a></strong> by <a href="https://leanpub.com/u/gojko">Gojko Adzic</a>, <a href="https://leanpub.com/u/davidevans_neuri">David Evans</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This is a book for anyone working in an iterative delivery environment, doing planning with user stories. The ideas in this book are useful both to people relatively new to user stories and those who have been working with them for years. People who work in software delivery, regardless of their role, will find plenty of tips for engaging stakeholders better and structuring iterative plans more effectively. Business stakeholders working with software teams will discover how to provide better information to their delivery groups, how to set better priorities and how to outrun the competition by achieving more with less software. - <a href="https://leanpub.com/50quickideas">Leanpub</a></p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="final-words">Final words</h3>

<p>The above recommendations are based on the books I’ve read and had a big influence on me. There many other great books which I didn’t heard off or I didn’t manage to read yet so please leave a comment with your recommendations.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-04-19T22:20:00+03:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Merge files using SDL Studio Project Automation API</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/03/11/Merge-translatable-files-using-SDL-Studio-Project-automation-api.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[SDL Studio allows the user to merge multiple files into one bilingual document (sdlxliff). This can be done during project creation and it can be useful in situations where you have multiple small files and you might want to translate them in one go without switching between documents.  If you don't already know SDL Studio is very extensible via the API's that are made available but sometimes simple things are not so simple to do by code because of software design decision or technical limitations. Merging files using SDL Studio Project Automation API can be done but is not that straight forward as you might expect and this is why I decided to write this article to show how this is done.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/03/11/Merge-translatable-files-using-SDL-Studio-Project-automation-api.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 21:20:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/03/11/Merge-translatable-files-using-SDL-Studio-Project-automation-api.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/merge-files/merge.jpg" alt="Click'n'Deploy" title="Merge files" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">SDL Studio allows the user to merge multiple files into one bilingual document (sdlxliff). This can be done during project creation and it can be useful in situations where you have multiple small files and you might want to translate them in one go without switching between documents. If you don't already know SDL Studio is very extensible via the API's that are made available but sometimes simple things are not so simple to do by code because of software design decision or technical limitations. Merging files using SDL Studio Project Automation API can be done but is not that straight forward as you might expect and this is why I decided to write this article to show how this is done.</p>

<h3 id="create-merged-project-file">Create Merged Project File</h3>

<p>Looking at the documentation you can easily find <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/ProjectAutomationApi/3.0/html/8c0d6583-c31c-365b-0819-ff19e18e1f5e.htm">CreateMergedProjectFile</a> method which allows you to specify the files you want to be merged and the name of the bilingual file which must have “.sdlxliff” extension. At this point this seems to be very simple but when you run this method you realize that is not actually doing much, there is no visible result on the project and the status is <em>Not Merged</em>. </p>

<h3 id="what-am-i-missing">What am I missing?</h3>

<p>At this point you only get an <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/ProjectAutomationApi/3.0/html/4ea34241-0524-aac3-45fa-817765b3bc5e.htm">MergedProjectFile</a> object which is just a representation of the merging structure. In order to actually create the bilingual merged file we need to use <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/FileTypeSupport/3.0/html/1f5584af-9763-46ff-894b-08127a2421a7.htm">Studio File Type Framework</a> to generate the sdlxliff file. Once we have that we can use <em>CopyToTargetLanguages</em> to copy the merged files to all target languages we need. To make this even more clear and concrete I’m going to share a sample code that is doing all the steps I’ve described until now.</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/af1242f60511c52fba79.js"></script>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>It’s not that complicated to merge files using the SDL Studio API but is not obvious and intuitive. I hope this article will clarify this situation. </p>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions or feedback.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-03-11T21:20:00+02:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sdl Studio PowerShell toolkit is now open source</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/02/18/Sdl-Studio-PowerShell-toolkit-open-source.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[Starting from today Sdl Studio powerhsell toolkit is open source and you can find it on github. The toolkit was written to facilitate scripting of the Project Automation API which comes with SDL Studio. Until now this was kept on the SDL internal TFS and you where only able to get it by going to the community forum. At this point you might ask yourself what's going to change from now on since the toolkit was freely distributed until now?]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/02/18/Sdl-Studio-PowerShell-toolkit-open-source.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2015 21:20:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/02/18/Sdl-Studio-PowerShell-toolkit-open-source.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/studio-powershell-toolkit/open-source.png" alt="Click'n'Deploy" title="Click'n'Deploy" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">Starting from today Sdl Studio powerhsell toolkit is open source and you can find it on github. The toolkit was written to facilitate scripting of the Project Automation API which comes with SDL Studio. Until now this was kept on the SDL internal TFS and you where only able to get it by going to the community forum. At this point you might ask yourself what's going to change from now on since the toolkit was freely distributed until now?</p>

<h3 id="github">Github</h3>

<p>The project is now hosted on github in this <a href="https://github.com/sdl/Sdl-studio-powershell-toolkit">location</a>. The internal TFS will no longer be used so this means that every change that will be made to the toolkit will be made on this repository including changes done by Sdl developers. Also this allows any interested developer to contribute to the toolkit. </p>

<p>Public releases are also hosted on github and you can be find them <a href="https://github.com/sdl/Sdl-studio-powershell-toolkit/releases/">here</a>. You are now able to download the entire toolkit or just one of the modules. </p>

<h3 id="open-source">Open source</h3>

<p>Open source it’s not at all equal to free, it’s much more than that. Yes you don’t have to pay any money for this toolkit but from now on is not only Sdl’s responsibility to maintain this toolkit, it’s also the responsibility of each toolkit user or developer. To be a bit more specific if you find bug or want a new feature you can log it <a href="https://github.com/sdl/Sdl-studio-powershell-toolkit/issues">here</a> but don’t necessarily expect someone from Sdl to resolve the issue, it might be anyone from the community or even you.</p>

<p>Another important aspect that comes with open source is that every change you made to this toolkit has to be made open source. It’s not mandatory to be made in the same repository but it has to be open source. I would encourage everyone to contribute to this repository and make the resolved issues available to everyone.</p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>Contribute to Sdl Studio PowerShell toolkit from <a href="https://github.com/sdl/Sdl-studio-powershell-toolkit">here</a> or download the latest release from <a href="https://github.com/sdl/Sdl-studio-powershell-toolkit/releases/tag/1.0.0.0">here</a>. </p>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions or feedback.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-02-18T21:20:00+02:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Click'n'Deploy Studio plugins</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/02/13/Click-n-deploy%20Studio%20plugins.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[App stores changed the way we install and maintain software on our devices. You now have a single centralized place where you go and search for what you need, click a button and in a matter of minutes you have the app working on your device. In a similar way you can extend SDL Studio by going on OpenExchange store and download a plugin you would like or need. Now this works just fine for most of the Studio plugins or apps but there are situations when you need to develop something that is specific for your company and doesn't make sense to be public to everyone since it's probably irrelevant for them and it might also contain confidential information. It would be nice if you would be able to create your private store inside OpenExchange where you can have you apps centralized and search-able just by you  but such a feature is not available at the moment. This article and video is about an alternate solution for this type of scenarios.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/02/13/Click-n-deploy%20Studio%20plugins.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2015 01:20:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/02/13/Click-n-deploy%20Studio%20plugins.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://speakerdeck.com/cromica/clickn-deploy" taget="_blank"><img src="/assets/images/posts//click-n-deploy/click-n-deploy.png" alt="Click'n'Deploy" title="Click'n'Deploy" class="img-responsive" /></a></p>

<p class="dropcap">App stores changed the way we install and maintain software on our devices. You now have a single centralized place where you go and search for what you need, click a button and in a matter of minutes you have the app working on your device. In a similar way you can extend SDL Studio by going on <a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/">OpenExchange</a> store and download a plugin you would like or need. Now this works just fine for most of the Studio plugins or apps but there are situations when you need to develop something that is specific for your company and doesn't make sense to be public to everyone since it's probably irrelevant for them and it might also contain confidential information. It would be nice if you would be able to create your private store inside <a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/">OpenExchange</a> where you can have you apps centralized and search-able just by you  but such a feature is not available at the moment. This article and video is about an alternate solution for this type of scenarios.</p>

<h3 id="the-solution">The solution</h3>

<p>The solution is very simple and is based on the idea to automate as much as possible the process of releasing you plugin. The exact same thing is promoted by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_delivery">Continuous Delivery</a>  practice and together with the evolution of this a couple of release management tools like <a href="https://octopusdeploy.com/">Octopus Deploy</a> or <a href="http://www.thoughtworks.com/products/go-continuous-delivery">GO</a> appeared in order to ease the adoption of such a practice. In our case since Studio plugins are developed using <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/net">Microsoft .Net</a> and it makes perfect sense to use <a href="https://octopusdeploy.com/">Octopus Deploy</a> since is dedicated for .Net solutions. Of course you can try and use <a href="http://www.thoughtworks.com/products/go-continuous-delivery">GO</a> or any other release management tool you prefer. If it’s not clear by now the solution I’m talking about is to automate your Studio plugin release management using <a href="https://octopusdeploy.com/">Octopus Deploy</a>.   </p>

<h3 id="octopus-deploy">Octopus Deploy</h3>

<p>I’m not going to cover in detail <a href="https://octopusdeploy.com/">Octopus Deploy</a> since it comes with a very good documentation, rather I’m going to present a higher level overview of how is going to work with Studio plugins. Octopus comes with a central server component which is called <a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Installing+Octopus">Octopus Deploy Server</a> that you need to install somewhere where all your users machines will be able to access it. It can be an internal private server, a public server or somewhere in a cloud platform, there is no limitation as long as it’s accessible. <a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Installing+Octopus">Octopus Deploy Server</a> comes with web user interface which you can use once you have the server installed. Besides the server component Octopus comes with a client component called <a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Installing+Tentacles">Tentacle Deploy agent</a>. This has to be installed on each user machine and it will be used to deploy your software, in our case the Studio plugins. This is a one time operation and once it’s done you will only use the web user interface that comes with the server. There is a third component called <a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Using+OctoPack">OctoPack</a> that is used to push the software/Studio plugin from you development or build machine to <a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Installing+Octopus">Octopus Deploy Server</a>.  </p>

<h3 id="clickndeploy-studio-plugins">Click’n’Deploy Studio plugins</h3>

<p>There are quit a few moving parts when you first setup <a href="https://octopusdeploy.com/">Octopus Deploy</a> and some of the steps might not that obvious so instead off writing them in this article I decided that it would be better if just create a video to show you exactly how you configure Octopus to release Studio plugins to the user machine. </p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mMDnY73D1x8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Useful learning resources:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Getting+started">Octopus Deploy Getting Started</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Installing+Octopus">Installing Octopus Deploy Server</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Installing+Tentacles">Installing Tentacles</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Using+OctoPack">Using OctoPack</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.nuget.org/">What is Nuget?</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/developer/sdk.html">Develop SDL Studio plugins</a></p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions or feedback.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-02-13T01:20:00+02:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <dc:date>2015-08-05T13:00:00+03:00</dc:date>
  </channel>
</rss>