<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd"
  xmlns:trackback="http://madskills.com/public/xml/rss/module/trackback/">
  <channel>
    <title>Romulus Crisan</title>
    <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com</link>
    <description>Romulus Crisan is a software developer, trainer, speaker, agile.</description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2015 22:20:00 +0300</pubDate>
    <item>
      <title>Studio plugin versioning</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/05/05/Studio%20plugin%20versioning.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[SDL Studio 2015 is just around the corner and as a plugin developer there are a few things you should do to make your plugin compatible with this new Studio version. Now with all Studio versions out there some may ask how can I control my plugin versions and how can I make sure my plugin will be used only by the appropriate version of SDL Studio.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/05/05/Studio%20plugin%20versioning.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2015 22:20:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/05/05/Studio%20plugin%20versioning.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/studio-plugin-versioning/version.jpg" alt="Studio plugin versioning" title="Studio plugin versioning" class="img-responsive"></p>

<p class="dropcap">SDL Studio 2015 is just around the corner and as a plugin developer there are a few things you should do to make your plugin compatible with this new Studio version. You can read more about this here: <a href="https://community.sdl.com/developers/language-developers/w/wiki/647.steps-to-upgrade-your-plugin-for-studio-2015">Steps to upgrade your plugin for Studio 2015</a>. Now with all Studio versions out there some may ask how can I control my plugin versions and how can I make sure my plugin will be used only by the appropriate version of SDL Studio.</p>

<h3>Plugin manifest</h3>

<p>Every plugin must contain a manifest file that defines a few general information about your plugin. The file is called <em>pluginpackage.manifest.xml</em> and if you open any *.sdlplugin file with and archiving tool, like <a href="http://www.7-zip.org/">7zip</a>, you should be able to see it and open it. Also when you create a new plugin solution in Microsoft Visual Studio this file will be automatically created for you and it will be included in our plugin package (.sdlplugin file). In this file you can add your plugin name, description, author, version, required product and you can <a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2014/11/07/3rd-party-assmeblies-and-SDL-Studio-plugins.html">specify additional files to be included in the package</a>.</p>

<h3>Plugin versioning</h3>

<p>As I highlighted before you can specify a plugin version by using the tag:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Version</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is used by SDL Studio to remove previously deployed plugins. For example if you have on your machine a plugin with version 0.1.0.0 if you install a new version like 0.1.1.0 it will automatically remove the unpacked version of the plugin and unpack the newer version. If the version is the same or lower this will not happen hence you will have to do it yourself.</p>

<h3>Product versioning</h3>

<p>Besides plugin versioning you can also specify SDL Studio versions that are compatible with your plugin. This can be done using the tag:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>RequiredProduct</p>
</blockquote>

<p>On this tag you can specify in the attribute <em>minversion</em> the lowest SDL Studio version that is compatible with your plugin. For example if you specify a minimum version of <em>10.0</em> this means that your plugin will be compatible with Studio 2011 or higher. If you want to limit your plugin just to a specific SDL Studio version you can also specify a <em>maxversion</em> attribute. So for example if in our case we add a maximum version of <em>10.9</em> this will not be compatible with Studio 2014 or higher and even if it&#39;s copied into the Studio 2014 plugins folder it will be ignored.</p>

<h3>Universal plugin installer</h3>

<p>The universal plugin installer is also using this information to avoid deploying plugins that are not compatible with a specific Studio version. If you are not familiar with the universal plugin installer you can read more here: <a href="https://github.com/sdl/Sdl-plugin-installer">SDL plugin installer</a>.</p>

<h3>Final words</h3>

<p>I recommend to review your manifest file and take advantage of the versioning capabilities. Even if there is no obvious reason at the moment it might prove handy in the future. </p>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-05-05T22:20:00+03:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code by the book</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/career/2015/04/19/Code-by-the-book.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[A few weeks back a friend of mine asked me to recommend him some programming/technical books. I was busy at that moment so I couldn't write my recommendations but he suggested that I should write an article on my blog. I thought that it's a great idea so here it is my list of recommendations. Although most of the times a I code in C# most of the books are technology agnostic which means every developer can read them.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/career/2015/04/19/Code-by-the-book.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2015 22:20:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/career/2015/04/19/Code-by-the-book.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/code-by-the-book/books.jpg" alt="Code by the book" title="Code by the book" class="img-responsive"></p>

<p class="dropcap">A few weeks back a friend of mine asked me to recommend him some programming/technical books. I was busy at that moment so I couldn't write my recommendations but he suggested that I should write an article on my blog. I thought that it's a great idea so here it is my list of recommendations. Although most of the times a I code in C# most of the books are technology agnostic which means every developer can read them.</p>

<h3>For blooming developers</h3>

<p>This are some of the books I recommend for developers which are just starting their career. It&#39;s not that they shouldn&#39;t read more advanced books but those might be a bit too difficult for the moment.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Clean-Code-Handbook-Software-Craftsmanship/dp/0132350882">Clean Code: A Handbook of Agile Software Craftsmanship</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Robert-C.-Martin/e/B000APG87E/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Robert C. Martin</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>The book is divided into three parts. The first describes the principles, patterns, and practices of writing clean code. The second part consists of several case studies of increasing complexity. Each case study is an exercise in cleaning up code—of transforming a code base that has some problems into one that is sound and efficient. The third part is the payoff: a single chapter containing a list of heuristics and “smells” gathered while creating the case studies. The result is a knowledge base that describes the way we think when we write, read, and clean code. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Clean-Code-Handbook-Software-Craftsmanship/dp/0132350882">Amazon</a> </p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Clean-Coder-Professional-Programmers/dp/0137081073">The Clean Coder: A Code of Conduct for Professional Programmers</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Robert-C.-Martin/e/B000APG87E/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Robert C. Martin</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>In The Clean Coder: A Code of Conduct for Professional Programmers, legendary software expert Robert C. Martin introduces the disciplines, techniques, tools, and practices of true software craftsmanship. This book is packed with practical advice–about everything from estimating and coding to refactoring and testing. It covers much more than technique: It is about attitude. Martin shows how to approach software development with honor, self-respect, and pride; work well and work clean; communicate and estimate faithfully; face difficult decisions with clarity and honesty; and understand that deep knowledge comes with a responsibility to act. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Clean-Coder-Professional-Programmers/dp/0137081073">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Depth-3rd-Edition-Jon-Skeet/dp/161729134X">C# in Depth, 3rd Edition</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Jon-Skeet/e/B001JP0M8K/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Jon Skeet</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>C# in Depth is a book for those who are passionate about C#. It aims to be a bridge between the existing introductory books and the language specification: something readable but detailed, exploring every aspect of the language from version 2 onwards. In the interests of brevity, it doesn&#39;t spend much time on C# 1 - readers are already expected to know the first version at least reasonably. Every new feature from C# 2 onwards is covered, however, as shown in the table of contents below. - <a href="http://csharpindepth.com/">C# in Depth</a></p>
</blockquote>

<h3>For experienced developers</h3>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Extreme-Programming-Explained-Embrace-Change/dp/0321278658/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475655&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=extreme+programming">Extreme Programming Explained: Embrace Change, 2nd Edition</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Kent-Beck/e/B000APC0EY/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Kent Beck</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>Whether you have a small team that is already closely aligned with your customers or a large team in a gigantic or multinational organization, you will find in these pages a wealth of ideas to challenge, inspire, and encourage you and your team members to substantially improve your software development. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Extreme-Programming-Explained-Embrace-Change/dp/0321278658/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475655&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=extreme+programming">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Implementation-Patterns-Kent-Beck/dp/0321413091/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475615&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=implementation+patterns">Implementation Patterns</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Kent-Beck/e/B000APC0EY/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Kent Beck</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>Implementation Patterns will help programmers at all experience levels, especially those who have benefited from software patterns or agile methods. It will also be an indispensable resource for development teams seeking to work together more efficiently and build more maintainable software. No other programming book will touch your day-to-day work more often. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Implementation-Patterns-Kent-Beck/dp/0321413091/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475615&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=implementation+patterns">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Domain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software/dp/0321125215/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475783&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=domain+driven+design">Domain-Driven Design: Tackling Complexity in the Heart of Software</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Eric-Evans/e/B001KDCO2I/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Eric Evans</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>This book provides a broad framework for making design decisions and a technical vocabulary for discussing domain design. It is a synthesis of widely accepted best practices along with the author’s own insights and experiences. Projects facing complex domains can use this framework to approach domain-driven design systematically. - <a href="http://dddcommunity.org/book/evans_2003/">DDDCommunity</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Code-Complete-Practical-Handbook-Construction/dp/0735619670/ref=sr_1_sc_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475928&amp;sr=1-1-spell&amp;keywords=code+comoplete">Code Complete: A Practical Handbook of Software Construction, Second Edition</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Steve-McConnell/e/B000APETRK/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Steve McConnell</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>Capturing the body of knowledge available from research, academia, and everyday commercial practice, McConnell synthesizes the most effective techniques and must-know principles into clear, pragmatic guidance. No matter what your experience level, development environment, or project size, this book will inform and stimulate your thinking—and help you build the highest quality code. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Code-Complete-Practical-Handbook-Construction/dp/0735619670/ref=sr_1_sc_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475928&amp;sr=1-1-spell&amp;keywords=code+comoplete">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Refactoring-Improving-Design-Existing-Code/dp/0201485672/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1429428810&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=refactoring+martin+fowler">Refactoring: Improving the Design of Existing Code</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Martin-Fowler/e/B000AQ6PGM/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Martin Fowler</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Kent-Beck/e/B000APC0EY/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_2">Kent Beck</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/s/ref=dp_byline_sr_book_3?ie=UTF8&amp;field-author=John+Brant&amp;search-alias=books&amp;text=John+Brant&amp;sort=relevancerank">John Brant</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/s/ref=dp_byline_sr_book_4?ie=UTF8&amp;field-author=William+Opdyke&amp;search-alias=books&amp;text=William+Opdyke&amp;sort=relevancerank">William Opdyke</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/s/ref=dp_byline_sr_book_5?ie=UTF8&amp;field-author=Don+Roberts&amp;search-alias=books&amp;text=Don+Roberts&amp;sort=relevancerank">Don Roberts</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>Refactoring is about improving the design of existing code. It is the process of changing a software system in such a way that it does not alter the external behavior of the code, yet improves its internal structure. With refactoring you can even take a bad design and rework it into a good one. This book offers a thorough discussion of the principles of refactoring, including where to spot opportunities for refactoring, and how to set up the required tests. There is also a catalog of more than 40 proven refactorings with details as to when and why to use the refactoring, step by step instructions for implementing it, and an example illustrating how it works The book is written using Java as its principle language, but the ideas are applicable to any OO language. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Refactoring-Improving-Design-Existing-Code/dp/0201485672/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1429428810&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=refactoring+martin+fowler">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Continuous-Delivery-Deployment-Automation-Addison-Wesley/dp/0321601912/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475911&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=continuous+delivery">Continuous Delivery: Reliable Software Releases through Build, Test, and Deployment Automation</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Jez-Humble/e/B003SNGS8E/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Jez Humble</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/David-Farley/e/B003VSTZ72/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_2">David Farley</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>Getting software released to users is often a painful, risky, and time-consuming process.
This groundbreaking new book sets out the principles and technical practices that enable
rapid, incremental delivery of high quality, valuable new functionality to users. Through
automation of the build, deployment, and testing process, and improved collaboration between
developers, testers, and operations, delivery teams can get changes released in a matter of hours—
sometimes even minutes–no matter what the size of a project or the complexity of its code base. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Continuous-Delivery-Deployment-Automation-Addison-Wesley/dp/0321601912/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475911&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=continuous+delivery">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Dependency-Injection-NET-Mark-Seemann/dp/1935182501/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475711&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=dependency+injection">Dependency Injection in .NET</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mark-Seemann/e/B004XYGMVK/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Mark Seemann</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>Dependency Injection in .NET introduces DI and provides a practical guide for applying it in .NET applications. The book presents the core patterns in plain C#, so you&#39;ll fully understand how DI works. Then you&#39;ll learn to integrate DI with standard Microsoft technologies like ASP.NET MVC, and to use DI frameworks like StructureMap, Castle Windsor, and Unity. By the end of the book, you&#39;ll be comfortable applying this powerful technique in your everyday .NET development. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Dependency-Injection-NET-Mark-Seemann/dp/1935182501/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475711&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=dependency+injection">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Art-Unit-Testing-examples/dp/1617290890/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475748&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=the+art+of+unit+testing">The Art of Unit Testing: with examples in C#</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Roy-Osherove/e/B00D3VXAG4/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Roy Osherove</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>The Art of Unit Testing, Second Edition guides you step by step from writing your first simple unit tests to building complete test sets that are maintainable, readable, and trustworthy. You&#39;ll move quickly to more complicated subjects like mocks and stubs, while learning to use isolation (mocking) frameworks like Moq, FakeItEasy, and Typemock Isolator. You&#39;ll explore test patterns and organization, refactor code applications, and learn how to test &quot;untestable&quot; code. Along the way, you&#39;ll learn about integration testing and techniques for testing with databases.</p>

<p>The examples in the book use C#, but will benefit anyone using a statically typed language such as Java or C++. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Art-Unit-Testing-examples/dp/1617290890/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425475748&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=the+art+of+unit+testing">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<h3>For those about to rock</h3>

<p>Software is about solving people problems and to do that you need more than just coding skills. If you want to rock you need to deliver the software as people expect it. On top of the technical books I recommend a few books that can help you rock.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/User-Stories-Applied-Software-Development/dp/0321205685">User Stories Applied: For Agile Software Development</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mike-Cohn/e/B001H6MN56/ref=dp_byline_cont_book_1">Mike Cohn</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>The best way to build software that meets users&#39; needs is to begin with &quot;user stories&quot;: simple, clear, brief descriptions of functionality that will be valuable to real users. In User Stories Applied, Mike Cohn provides you with a front-to-back blueprint for writing these user stories and weaving them into your development lifecycle. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/User-Stories-Applied-Software-Development/dp/0321205685">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Impact-Mapping-software-products-projects-ebook/dp/B009KWDKVA">Impact Mapping: Making a big impact with software products and projects</a></strong> by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Gojko-Adzic/e/B004P9W8G6/ref=ntt_athr_dp_pel_1">Gojko Adzic</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>This handbook is a practical guide to impact mapping, a simple yet incredibly effective method for collaborative strategic planning that helps organisations make an impact with software. Impact mapping helps to create better plans and roadmaps that ensure alignment of business and delivery, and are easily adaptable to change. Impact mapping fits nicely into several current trends in software product management and release planning, including goal-oriented requirements engineering, frequent iterative delivery, agile and lean software methods, lean startup product development cycles, and design thinking. - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Impact-Mapping-software-products-projects-ebook/dp/B009KWDKVA">Amazon</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong><a href="https://leanpub.com/50quickideas">Fifty Quick Ideas to Improve your User Stories</a></strong> by <a href="https://leanpub.com/u/gojko">Gojko Adzic</a>, <a href="https://leanpub.com/u/davidevans_neuri">David Evans</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>This is a book for anyone working in an iterative delivery environment, doing planning with user stories. The ideas in this book are useful both to people relatively new to user stories and those who have been working with them for years. People who work in software delivery, regardless of their role, will find plenty of tips for engaging stakeholders better and structuring iterative plans more effectively. Business stakeholders working with software teams will discover how to provide better information to their delivery groups, how to set better priorities and how to outrun the competition by achieving more with less software. - <a href="https://leanpub.com/50quickideas">Leanpub</a></p>
</blockquote>

<h3>Final words</h3>

<p>The above recommendations are based on the books I&#39;ve read and had a big influence on me. There many other great books which I didn&#39;t heard off or I didn&#39;t manage to read yet so please leave a comment with your recommendations.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-04-19T22:20:00+03:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Merge files using SDL Studio Project Automation API</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/03/11/Merge-translatable-files-using-SDL-Studio-Project-automation-api.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[SDL Studio allows the user to merge multiple files into one bilingual document (sdlxliff). This can be done during project creation and it can be useful in situations where you have multiple small files and you might want to translate them in one go without switching between documents.  If you don't already know SDL Studio is very extensible via the API's that are made available but sometimes simple things are not so simple to do by code because of software design decision or technical limitations. Merging files using SDL Studio Project Automation API can be done but is not that straight forward as you might expect and this is why I decided to write this article to show how this is done.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/03/11/Merge-translatable-files-using-SDL-Studio-Project-automation-api.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 21:20:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/03/11/Merge-translatable-files-using-SDL-Studio-Project-automation-api.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/merge-files/merge.jpg" alt="Click'n'Deploy" title="Merge files" class="img-responsive"></p>

<p class="dropcap">SDL Studio allows the user to merge multiple files into one bilingual document (sdlxliff). This can be done during project creation and it can be useful in situations where you have multiple small files and you might want to translate them in one go without switching between documents. If you don't already know SDL Studio is very extensible via the API's that are made available but sometimes simple things are not so simple to do by code because of software design decision or technical limitations. Merging files using SDL Studio Project Automation API can be done but is not that straight forward as you might expect and this is why I decided to write this article to show how this is done.</p>

<h3>Create Merged Project File</h3>

<p>Looking at the documentation you can easily find <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/ProjectAutomationApi/3.0/html/8c0d6583-c31c-365b-0819-ff19e18e1f5e.htm">CreateMergedProjectFile</a> method which allows you to specify the files you want to be merged and the name of the bilingual file which must have &quot;.sdlxliff&quot; extension. At this point this seems to be very simple but when you run this method you realize that is not actually doing much, there is no visible result on the project and the status is <em>Not Merged</em>. </p>

<h3>What am I missing?</h3>

<p>At this point you only get an <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/ProjectAutomationApi/3.0/html/4ea34241-0524-aac3-45fa-817765b3bc5e.htm">MergedProjectFile</a> object which is just a representation of the merging structure. In order to actually create the bilingual merged file we need to use <a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/FileTypeSupport/3.0/html/1f5584af-9763-46ff-894b-08127a2421a7.htm">Studio File Type Framework</a> to generate the sdlxliff file. Once we have that we can use <em>CopyToTargetLanguages</em> to copy the merged files to all target languages we need. To make this even more clear and concrete I&#39;m going to share a sample code that is doing all the steps I&#39;ve described until now.</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/af1242f60511c52fba79.js"></script>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>It&#39;s not that complicated to merge files using the SDL Studio API but is not obvious and intuitive. I hope this article will clarify this situation. </p>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions or feedback.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-03-11T21:20:00+02:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sdl Studio PowerShell toolkit is now open source</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/02/18/Sdl-Studio-PowerShell-toolkit-open-source.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[Starting from today Sdl Studio powerhsell toolkit is open source and you can find it on github. The toolkit was written to facilitate scripting of the Project Automation API which comes with SDL Studio. Until now this was kept on the SDL internal TFS and you where only able to get it by going to the community forum. At this point you might ask yourself what's going to change from now on since the toolkit was freely distributed until now?]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/02/18/Sdl-Studio-PowerShell-toolkit-open-source.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2015 21:20:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/02/18/Sdl-Studio-PowerShell-toolkit-open-source.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/studio-powershell-toolkit/open-source.png" alt="Click'n'Deploy" title="Click'n'Deploy" class="img-responsive"></p>

<p class="dropcap">Starting from today Sdl Studio powerhsell toolkit is open source and you can find it on github. The toolkit was written to facilitate scripting of the Project Automation API which comes with SDL Studio. Until now this was kept on the SDL internal TFS and you where only able to get it by going to the community forum. At this point you might ask yourself what's going to change from now on since the toolkit was freely distributed until now?</p>

<h3>Github</h3>

<p>The project is now hosted on github in this <a href="https://github.com/sdl/Sdl-studio-powershell-toolkit">location</a>. The internal TFS will no longer be used so this means that every change that will be made to the toolkit will be made on this repository including changes done by Sdl developers. Also this allows any interested developer to contribute to the toolkit. </p>

<p>Public releases are also hosted on github and you can be find them <a href="https://github.com/sdl/Sdl-studio-powershell-toolkit/releases/">here</a>. You are now able to download the entire toolkit or just one of the modules. </p>

<h3>Open source</h3>

<p>Open source it&#39;s not at all equal to free, it&#39;s much more than that. Yes you don&#39;t have to pay any money for this toolkit but from now on is not only Sdl&#39;s responsibility to maintain this toolkit, it&#39;s also the responsibility of each toolkit user or developer. To be a bit more specific if you find bug or want a new feature you can log it <a href="https://github.com/sdl/Sdl-studio-powershell-toolkit/issues">here</a> but don&#39;t necessarily expect someone from Sdl to resolve the issue, it might be anyone from the community or even you.</p>

<p>Another important aspect that comes with open source is that every change you made to this toolkit has to be made open source. It&#39;s not mandatory to be made in the same repository but it has to be open source. I would encourage everyone to contribute to this repository and make the resolved issues available to everyone.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>Contribute to Sdl Studio PowerShell toolkit from <a href="https://github.com/sdl/Sdl-studio-powershell-toolkit">here</a> or download the latest release from <a href="https://github.com/sdl/Sdl-studio-powershell-toolkit/releases/tag/1.0.0.0">here</a>. </p>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions or feedback.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-02-18T21:20:00+02:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Click'n'Deploy Studio plugins</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/02/13/Click-n-deploy%20Studio%20plugins.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[App stores changed the way we install and maintain software on our devices. You now have a single centralized place where you go and search for what you need, click a button and in a matter of minutes you have the app working on your device. In a similar way you can extend SDL Studio by going on OpenExchange store and download a plugin you would like or need. Now this works just fine for most of the Studio plugins or apps but there are situations when you need to develop something that is specific for your company and doesn't make sense to be public to everyone since it's probably irrelevant for them and it might also contain confidential information. It would be nice if you would be able to create your private store inside OpenExchange where you can have you apps centralized and search-able just by you  but such a feature is not available at the moment. This article and video is about an alternate solution for this type of scenarios.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/02/13/Click-n-deploy%20Studio%20plugins.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2015 01:20:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/02/13/Click-n-deploy%20Studio%20plugins.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://speakerdeck.com/cromica/clickn-deploy" taget="_blank"><img src="/assets/images/posts//click-n-deploy/click-n-deploy.png" alt="Click'n'Deploy" title="Click'n'Deploy" class="img-responsive"></a></p>

<p class="dropcap">App stores changed the way we install and maintain software on our devices. You now have a single centralized place where you go and search for what you need, click a button and in a matter of minutes you have the app working on your device. In a similar way you can extend SDL Studio by going on <a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/">OpenExchange</a> store and download a plugin you would like or need. Now this works just fine for most of the Studio plugins or apps but there are situations when you need to develop something that is specific for your company and doesn't make sense to be public to everyone since it's probably irrelevant for them and it might also contain confidential information. It would be nice if you would be able to create your private store inside <a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/">OpenExchange</a> where you can have you apps centralized and search-able just by you  but such a feature is not available at the moment. This article and video is about an alternate solution for this type of scenarios.</p>

<h3>The solution</h3>

<p>The solution is very simple and is based on the idea to automate as much as possible the process of releasing you plugin. The exact same thing is promoted by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_delivery">Continuous Delivery</a>  practice and together with the evolution of this a couple of release management tools like <a href="https://octopusdeploy.com/">Octopus Deploy</a> or <a href="http://www.thoughtworks.com/products/go-continuous-delivery">GO</a> appeared in order to ease the adoption of such a practice. In our case since Studio plugins are developed using <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/net">Microsoft .Net</a> and it makes perfect sense to use <a href="https://octopusdeploy.com/">Octopus Deploy</a> since is dedicated for .Net solutions. Of course you can try and use <a href="http://www.thoughtworks.com/products/go-continuous-delivery">GO</a> or any other release management tool you prefer. If it&#39;s not clear by now the solution I&#39;m talking about is to automate your Studio plugin release management using <a href="https://octopusdeploy.com/">Octopus Deploy</a>.   </p>

<h3>Octopus Deploy</h3>

<p>I&#39;m not going to cover in detail <a href="https://octopusdeploy.com/">Octopus Deploy</a> since it comes with a very good documentation, rather I&#39;m going to present a higher level overview of how is going to work with Studio plugins. Octopus comes with a central server component which is called <a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Installing+Octopus">Octopus Deploy Server</a> that you need to install somewhere where all your users machines will be able to access it. It can be an internal private server, a public server or somewhere in a cloud platform, there is no limitation as long as it&#39;s accessible. <a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Installing+Octopus">Octopus Deploy Server</a> comes with web user interface which you can use once you have the server installed. Besides the server component Octopus comes with a client component called <a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Installing+Tentacles">Tentacle Deploy agent</a>. This has to be installed on each user machine and it will be used to deploy your software, in our case the Studio plugins. This is a one time operation and once it&#39;s done you will only use the web user interface that comes with the server. There is a third component called <a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Using+OctoPack">OctoPack</a> that is used to push the software/Studio plugin from you development or build machine to <a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Installing+Octopus">Octopus Deploy Server</a>.  </p>

<h3>Click&#39;n&#39;Deploy Studio plugins</h3>

<p>There are quit a few moving parts when you first setup <a href="https://octopusdeploy.com/">Octopus Deploy</a> and some of the steps might not that obvious so instead off writing them in this article I decided that it would be better if just create a video to show you exactly how you configure Octopus to release Studio plugins to the user machine. </p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mMDnY73D1x8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p>Useful learning resources:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Getting+started">Octopus Deploy Getting Started</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Installing+Octopus">Installing Octopus Deploy Server</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Installing+Tentacles">Installing Tentacles</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://docs.octopusdeploy.com/display/OD/Using+OctoPack">Using OctoPack</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.nuget.org/">What is Nuget?</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/developer/sdk.html">Develop SDL Studio plugins</a></p></li>
</ol>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions or feedback.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-02-13T01:20:00+02:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to access segment tags using Studio File Type Framework</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/01/06/How%20to%20access%20segment%20tags%20using%20Studio%20File%20Type%20Framework%20.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[Accessing segment tags might not be something you have to do everyday but there might be some scenarios where you need to manipulate the tags of your segments. This can be done using Studio File Type Framework which is part of the Studio SDK. The documentation is providing an overview of the entire framework and also includes high level overview of what I'm going to discuss in this article."]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/01/06/How%20to%20access%20segment%20tags%20using%20Studio%20File%20Type%20Framework%20.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2015 18:20:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/01/06/How%20to%20access%20segment%20tags%20using%20Studio%20File%20Type%20Framework%20.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/segmentTags/segments.png" alt="Assembly Resolver" title="Assembly Resolver" class="img-responsive"></p>

<p class="dropcap">Accessing segment tags might not be something you have to do everyday but there might be some scenarios where you need to manipulate the tags of your segments. This can be done using Studio File Type Framework which is part of the Studio SDK. The documentation is providing an overview of the entire framework and also includes high level overview of what I'm going to discuss in this article. </p>

<h3>Visitor Pattern</h3>

<p>Before jumping into the problem I recommend you to get familiarized with the visitor pattern since this is used as part of the Studio File Type Framework and you will need apply it in order to get the tags. To get familiarized you can read the theory on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Visitor_pattern">wikipedia</a> or if you want a practical example you can have a look <a href="http://www.codeproject.com/Articles/588882/TheplusVisitorplusPatternplusExplained">here</a>.</p>

<p>In Studio File Type Framework visitor pattern is made available via <em>IMarkupDataVisitor</em> interface. </p>

<h3>Paragraphs, Segments and more</h3>

<p>When a document is opened for translation Studio brakes it into segments. This is done by the segmentation engine using the segmentation rules defined in Studio. A segment can be a paragraph or a sentence length but what is important to understand is that for Studio a segment represents a piece of localizable content for which existing translations can possibly be used. Besides localizable content there are other elements, like formatting, that Studio needs to take into considerations.</p>

<p>Now that we have a better understanding of how Studio is handling the content let me highlight how this is reflected in the File Type Framework:</p>

<p><code>IParagraph</code> represents the entire content that is displayed on one Studio editor row. This can contain multiple elements like tags or segments.</p>

<p><code>IParagraphUnit</code> a unit of source language content and the localized target language content. Source and Target can be accessed using the corresponding properties which will return an <em>IParagraph</em> object instance with the information described above. One thing to keep in mind is that there are two type of paragraph units:</p>

<ol>
<li>Structure paragraph units will contain only structure tags that are not localizable. In this case the Target will be null.</li>
<li>Localizable paragraph units will contain localizable content.</li>
</ol>

<p><code>ISegment</code> represents a piece of localizable content.</p>

<p><code>ISegmentPair</code> segments exists in source and target language versions which are bot accessible using <em>ISegmentPair</em>. </p>

<p>Segments and Paragraphs are considered containers of other elements like text, comments, revisions and so on. All containers share common behavior and that&#39;s why in the File Type Framework both are abstracted using <em>IAbstractMarkupDataContainer</em>. An <em>IAbstractMarkupDataContainer</em> contains multiple <em>IAbstractMarkupData</em> elements. This means that text, comments and other similar elements are represented in the framework using <em>IAbstractMarkupData</em> interface. One very important aspect of this structure is the fact that a segment can be considered as an element of the paragraph but also as a container for other elements which means that it can be manipulated as an <em>IAbstractMarkupDataContainer</em> or as an <em>IAbstractMarkupData</em>.</p>

<p>Here&#39;s a diagram which describes the structure:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/segmentTags/abstractmarkupdatacontainer.png" alt="Abstract Markup Data Container" title="Abstract Markup Data Container" class="img-responsive"></p>

<h3>Access segment tags</h3>

<p>All paragraph elements are like a tree structure that must be traversed using visitor pattern. For each paragraph unit we can look at the Source property which is an <em>IParagraph</em>. Thinking at the abstraction I was talking earlier an <em>IParagraph</em> is in essence an <em>IAbstractMarkupDataContainer</em> which in turn is an enumeration of <em>IAbstractMarkupData</em>. Here&#39;s a sample code on how you can iterate paragraph unit elements:</p>

<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-csharp" data-lang="csharp"><span class="n">IEnumerable</span><span class="p">&lt;</span><span class="n">IAbstractMarkupData</span><span class="p">&gt;</span> <span class="n">container</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">paragraphUnit</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">Source</span><span class="p">;</span>
 
<span class="k">foreach</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">var</span> <span class="n">contentItem</span> <span class="k">in</span> <span class="n">container</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="c1">//structure tag is not supported by IMarkupDataVisitor and you should ignore it</span>
    <span class="n">IStructureTag</span> <span class="n">stag</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">contentItem</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">IStructureTag</span><span class="p">;</span>
       <span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">stag</span> <span class="p">==</span> <span class="k">null</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">continue</span><span class="p">;</span>
                       
      <span class="n">contentItem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">AcceptVisitor</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">new</span> <span class="n">MarkupDataVisitor</span><span class="p">());</span>
<span class="p">}</span></code></pre></div>

<p>There is one new thing in the above sample which I didn&#39;t discuss about.This is <em>MarkupDataVisitor</em> which is an implementation of the interface <em>IMarkupDataVisitor</em> I was mentioning in the visitor pattern section. Here&#39;s how the interface looks like:</p>

<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-csharp" data-lang="csharp"><span class="c1">/// &lt;summary&gt;</span>
<span class="c1">/// Interface for the visitor in the visitor pattern implementation for translatable source / target </span>
<span class="c1">/// content items in a localizable paragraph unit.</span>
<span class="c1">/// &lt;/summary&gt;</span>
<span class="k">public</span> <span class="k">interface</span> <span class="n">IMarkupDataVisitor</span>
<span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// Called by tag pair instances.</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;/summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;param name=&quot;tagPair&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;</span>
    <span class="k">void</span> <span class="nf">VisitTagPair</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ITagPair</span> <span class="n">tagPair</span><span class="p">);</span>


    <span class="c1">/// &lt;summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// Called by placeholder tag instances.</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;/summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;param name=&quot;tag&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;</span>
    <span class="k">void</span> <span class="nf">VisitPlaceholderTag</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">IPlaceholderTag</span> <span class="n">tag</span><span class="p">);</span>


    <span class="c1">/// &lt;summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// Called by text instances.</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;/summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;param name=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;</span>
    <span class="k">void</span> <span class="nf">VisitText</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">IText</span> <span class="n">text</span><span class="p">);</span>


    <span class="c1">/// &lt;summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// Called by segment instances.</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;/summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;param name=&quot;segment&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;</span>
    <span class="k">void</span> <span class="nf">VisitSegment</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ISegment</span> <span class="n">segment</span><span class="p">);</span>


    <span class="c1">/// &lt;summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// Called by location marker instances.</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;/summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;param name=&quot;location&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;</span>
    <span class="k">void</span> <span class="nf">VisitLocationMarker</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ILocationMarker</span> <span class="n">location</span><span class="p">);</span>


    <span class="c1">/// &lt;summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// Called by comment marker instances.</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;/summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;param name=&quot;commentMarker&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;</span>
    <span class="k">void</span> <span class="nf">VisitCommentMarker</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ICommentMarker</span> <span class="n">commentMarker</span><span class="p">);</span>


    <span class="c1">/// &lt;summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// Called by other marker instances.</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;/summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;param name=&quot;marker&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;</span>
    <span class="k">void</span> <span class="nf">VisitOtherMarker</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">IOtherMarker</span> <span class="n">marker</span><span class="p">);</span>


    <span class="c1">/// &lt;summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// Called by locked content instances.</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;/summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;param name=&quot;lockedContent&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;</span>
    <span class="k">void</span> <span class="nf">VisitLockedContent</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ILockedContent</span> <span class="n">lockedContent</span><span class="p">);</span>


    <span class="c1">/// &lt;summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// Called by revision marker instances.</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;/summary&gt;</span>
    <span class="c1">/// &lt;param name=&quot;revisionMarker&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;</span>
    <span class="k">void</span> <span class="nf">VisitRevisionMarker</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">IRevisionMarker</span> <span class="n">revisionMarker</span><span class="p">);</span>
<span class="p">}</span></code></pre></div>

<p>As you can see you are now able manipulate each element type. For example if you need formatting information you can get it from the <em>ITagPair</em> interface. </p>

<p><strong>Don&#39;t forget</strong> that segments are containers as well so on <em>VisitSegement</em> method you need to traverse his structure in the same way as for the paragraph unit.</p>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions or feedback.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-01-06T18:20:00+02:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SDL Studio standalone plugin assembly resolver</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2014/11/28/SDL-Studio-standalone-plugin-assembly-resolve.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[SDL Studio plugin system allows developers to develop new features on top of the standard functionality. There are 2 types of plugins that can be developed, one which behaves like a Studio add-in and another one which behaves as a standalone application. Both plugin types require to run inside Studio installation folder. This is because the public Studio SDK is using other assemblies that are located in Studio folder. While this is perfectly fine for add-in type plugins for standalone plugins this adds limitation on where and how you can deploy your application.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2014/11/28/SDL-Studio-standalone-plugin-assembly-resolve.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 14:20:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2014/11/28/SDL-Studio-standalone-plugin-assembly-resolve.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/assemblyresolver/assemblyresolver.jpg" alt="Assembly Resolver" title="Assembly Resolver" class="img-responsive"></p>

<p class="dropcap">SDL Studio plugin system allows developers to develop new features on top of the standard functionality. There are 2 types of plugins that can be developed, one which behaves like a Studio add-in and another one which behaves as a standalone application. Both plugin types require to run inside Studio installation folder. This is because the public Studio SDK is using other assemblies that are located in Studio folder. While this is perfectly fine for add-in type plugins for standalone plugins this adds limitation on where and how you can deploy your application.</p>

<h3>Why not GAC ?</h3>

<p>Many developers have asked us to register Studio assemblies in <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/yf1d93sz%28v=vs.110%29.aspx">GAC</a> in order to solve the issue on where and how you can deploy your standalone Studio plugins. Having Studio assemblies registered in <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/yf1d93sz%28v=vs.110%29.aspx">GAC</a> means that those assembly can be shared across the entire system. Although registering assemblies in GAC might had seem to be a good solution there are many implications when doing it. The main reason why Studio is not using <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/yf1d93sz%28v=vs.110%29.aspx">GAC</a> is because of the following scenario:</p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>GAC supports multiple version of an assembly. This means that when an assembly is updated to a newer version both versions will be saved. You might say that the old version should be removed, but this is not always possible since for example there are customers that have multiple version of Studio that are used on the same machine. Keeping multiple version of the same assembly will lead to unexpected behavior and errors from the application.</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p>You can read more about why to avoid GAC <a href="http://www.sellsbrothers.com/Posts/Details/12503">here</a>.   </p>

<h3>Got it ... no GAC, but we want solutions!</h3>

<p>To solve this problem I&#39;ve developed a small library called <strong>Studio AssemblyResolver</strong>. Basically every time an dll is not found in the current application location the library will look after the dll in the Studio folder. The library comes with 2 mechanism for looking after Studio folder but you can add your own resolve mechanism. If you are interested about more details please have a look <a href="https://github.com/cromica/Studio-AssemblyResolver">here</a>. The library is also published in the <a href="https://www.nuget.org/packages/Studio.AssemblyResolver/0.1.1">Nuget package repository</a> which allows to be easily added to your project.</p>

<h3>How to use Studio AssemblyResolver</h3>

<p>There are 2 simple steps to get your Studio assemblies resolved:</p>

<ul>
<li>Add a reference to the <strong>Studio.AssemblyResolver</strong> library from Visual Studio using NuGet</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/assemblyresolver/managenuget.png" alt="Manage Nuget" title="Manage Nuget" class="img-responsive"></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/assemblyresolver/nugetassemblyresolver.png" alt="Nuget assembly resolver" title="Nuget assembly resolver" class="img-responsive"></p>

<ul>
<li>Add the following line of code in you application entry point</li>
</ul>

<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-csharp" data-lang="csharp"><span class="n">AssemblyResolver</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">Resolve</span><span class="p">();</span></code></pre></div>

<p>I&#39;ve already included the <strong>Studio AssemblyResolver</strong> library in <a href="https://github.com/sdl/SDL-Community/tree/master/Reindex%20Translation%20Memories">Reindex Translation Memories</a> plugin. You can have a look <a href="https://github.com/sdl/SDL-Community/blob/master/Reindex%20Translation%20Memories/Sdl.Community.ReindexTms/Program.cs#L18">here</a> if you are interested to see how I&#39;ve included the library.</p>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions or feedback.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2014-11-28T14:20:00+02:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3rd party assemblies and SDL Studio plugins</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2014/11/07/3rd-party-assmeblies-and-SDL-Studio-plugins.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[Last week I was working at a new plugin for SDL Studio 2014 and I wanted to serialize some information in json. The best tool handle this type of operations in .NET, at least in my opinion, is Json.NET. It made perfect sense to use it but until now I didn't use any external dependencies in an SDL Studio plugin so I started to look into what options we have to deploy our plugins together with 3rd party assemblies.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2014/11/07/3rd-party-assmeblies-and-SDL-Studio-plugins.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2014 18:18:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2014/11/07/3rd-party-assmeblies-and-SDL-Studio-plugins.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/3rdparty/3rdpartyassemblies.png" alt="Hello SDL" title="Hello SDL" class="img-responsive"></p>

<p class="dropcap">Last week I was working at a new plugin for SDL Studio 2014 and I wanted to serialize some information in json. The best tool handle this type of operations in .NET, at least in my opinion, is <a href="http://james.newtonking.com/json" target="_blank">Json.NET</a>. It made perfect sense to use it but until now I didn't use any external dependencies in an SDL Studio plugin so I started to look into what options we have to deploy our plugins together with 3rd party assemblies.</p>

<h3>SDL Studio plugins</h3>

<p>This is not a detailed look at what SDL Studio plugins are but I want to give a bit of context on how they are working. First of all each plugin has to be packed in a package with extension <code>.sldplugin</code> (this a zip file in essence). If you use the SDL Studio templates from Visual Studio this done for you automatically. Once you have the package you need to deploy it in one of the three location where SDL Studio is expecting plugins:</p>

<blockquote>
<ol>
<li><p>$(CurrentUser)\AppData\Local\SDL\SDL Trados Studio{Studio Version}\Plugins\Packages\</p></li>
<li><p>$(CurrentUser)\AppData\Roaming\SDL\SDL Trados Studio{Studio Version}\Plugins\Packages\</p></li>
<li><p>$(ProgramData)\SDL\SDL Trados Studio{Studio Version}\Plugins\Packages\</p></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>There is no difference between this locations so you can choose whatever you prefer. Once the package is in one of this locations when SDL Studio starts it will unpack the package, drop the content into a dedicated location and load the plugin assembly. This depends on where you deployed your package and can be one of this locations:</p>

<blockquote>
<ol>
<li><p>$(CurrentUser)\AppData\Local\SDL\SDL Trados Studio{Studio Version}\Plugins\Unpacked\</p></li>
<li><p>$(CurrentUser)\AppData\Roaming\SDL\SDL Trados Studio{Studio Version}\Plugins\Unpacked\</p></li>
<li><p>$(ProgramData)\SDL\SDL Trados Studio{Studio Version}\Plugins\Unpacked\</p></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<h3>Deploy 3rd party assemblies</h3>

<p>Now that we have a brief understanding on how SDL Studio handles plugins let&#39;s see what options we have to deploy 3rd party plugins:</p>

<blockquote>
<ol>
<li><p>Include the assemblies in the plugin package</p></li>
<li><p>Create an installer which will copy the 3rd party assemblies into SDL Studio folder under $(ProgramFiles)</p></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>Although the second option can work I don&#39;t like it because it requires more work, administrative rights to deploy the assemblies and might intefere with Studio installation. This was also suggest by <a href="https://community.sdl.com/members/davidfritch/default.aspx">David Fritch</a> in this <a href="https://community.sdl.com/phase_2_groups/sdl_openexchange_developers/f/39/t/3149.aspx">thread</a> as a possible way to do it.</p>

<p>I consider the first option the right way to do it since it&#39;s very simple and clean. All you have to do is change the <code>pluginpackage.manifest.xml</code> which has to be part of the solution in order to generate the <code>.sdlplugin</code> file. By default this xml file contains some tags to specify the plugin name, version, description, author and required SDL Studio product. You will need to add an <code>&lt;Include&gt;</code> tag which in my case, for <a href="http://james.newtonking.com/json">Json.NET</a>, looked something like this:</p>

<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-xml" data-lang="xml"><span class="nt">&lt;Include&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;File&gt;</span>Newtonsoft.Json.dll<span class="nt">&lt;/File&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;/Include&gt;</span></code></pre></div>
 

<p>You can have a look at my entire xml file <a href="https://github.com/sdl/SDL-Community/blob/master/Controlled%20Machine%20Translation%20Providers/Sdl.Community.ControlledMTProviders/pluginpackage.manifest.xml#L9">here</a>.</p>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions or feedback.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2014-11-07T18:18:00+02:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Codecamp 2014</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/speaker/2014/10/31/Codecamp-2014.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[One of my personal objectives for this year was to attend as a speaker to local community developer conferences. Most known,at least by me, are ITCamp and Codecamp. ITCamp is held once a year in Cluj-Napoca and Codecamp is held twice a year in Iasi, although there are some smaller Codecamp events in Cluj those are not related. I'm really happy that this year I had the opportunity to participate at all 3 events, so a big big thanks to the organizers for having me.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/speaker/2014/10/31/Codecamp-2014.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2014 11:07:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/speaker/2014/10/31/Codecamp-2014.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="owl-carousel text-left" data-navigation="true" data-singleitem="true" data-autoplay="true" data-transition="fade">
    <div class="item dragCursor">
        <img src="/assets/images/posts/codecamp2014/1.jpg" class="img-responsive"  alt="img" />
    </div>
    <div class="item dragCursor">
        <img src="/assets/images/posts/codecamp2014/2.jpg" class="img-responsive" alt="img" />
    </div>
    <div class="item dragCursor">
        <img src="/assets/images/posts/codecamp2014/3.jpg" class="img-responsive" alt="img" />
    </div>
    <div class="item dragCursor">
        <img src="/assets/images/posts/codecamp2014/4.jpg" class="img-responsive" alt="img" />
    </div>
    <div class="item dragCursor">
        <img src="/assets/images/posts/codecamp2014/5.jpg" class="img-responsive" alt="img" />
    </div>
</div>                  

<p class="dropcap">One of my personal objectives for this year was to attend as a speaker to local community developer conferences. Most known,at least by me, are ITCamp and Codecamp. ITCamp is held once a year in Cluj-Napoca and Codecamp is held twice a year in Iasi, although there are some smaller Codecamp events in Cluj those are not related. I'm really happy that this year I had the opportunity to participate at all 3 events, so a big big thanks to the organizers for having me.</p>

<h3>Codecamp</h3>

<p>I&#39;ve never been to Iasi until this year and I can&#39;t say that I&#39;ve seen too much of it since both times I&#39;ve been there I was caught up with <a href="http://iasi.codecamp.ro/">Codecamp</a> event. Although I&#39;ve haven&#39;t seen much of the city I&#39;ve met really nice people which are really passionate about software industry. Each event had more than 1400 participants which I believe it&#39;s a really big achievement. The fact that there is no fee to participate at the conference opened the door even to students which had a great opportunity to get in touch with the industry and basically their future. The event is also for seniors who can find lots interesting topics and a good place to network.</p>

<p>For me <a href="http://iasi.codecamp.ro/">Codecamp</a> was a nice experience and I can&#39;t wait for the next edition which will probably happen in spring 2015. Kudos to <a href="https://ro.linkedin.com/in/cardasim">Florin Cardasim</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gabrielenea">Gabriel Enea</a> and <a href="http://ro.linkedin.com/in/dannicola">Dan Nicola</a> who believed in their ideas and made this possible.</p>

<h3>My sessions</h3>

<p>I had two session which I presented this year at <a href="http://iasi.codecamp.ro/">Codecamp</a>. The first one which I&#39;ve done in may is <strong>Information Exchange using Hybrid Azure Integration</strong>. In this session I&#39;m talking about ways we can integrate on-premise LOB applications with azure cloud solutions based on messaging pattern. The second session which I had last weekend is <strong>Click&#39;n&#39;Deploy</strong>. This one was done together with <a href="http://www.radupascal.com/">Radu Pascal</a> and it was my first duet session. In this talk we present our approach on enabling continuous integration and continuous deployment using <a href="http://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/get-started/build-your-apps-vs.aspx">TFS Build</a>, <a href="http://gulpjs.com/">Gulp</a> and <a href="https://octopusdeploy.com/">Octopus Deploy</a>. During the session we showed how we&#39;ve implemented it in a real life example.</p>

<p>If want to see more pictures have a look <a href="https://plus.google.com/photos/107459365520380827818/albums/6076078203903397409">here</a>.</p>

<h3>Information Exchange using Hybrid Azure Integration slides</h3>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="6ed4e240af78013157f156ebe6298001" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>

<h3>Click&#39;n&#39;Deploy slides</h3>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="b0db24f042710132bd3a62fe72f26203" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions or feedback. If you are interested in presenting this sessions just send me an email.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2014-10-31T11:07:00+02:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hello SDL</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/career/2014/10/01/hello-sdl.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[I now have two weeks since I joined SDL as a Language Platform Evangelist Developer. Almost everyone asked me what does that mean and what will I do so I decided that I better explain here in detail. If you are looking for a general definition of the position you can find one on wikipedia but it won't help you too much. In order to understand it better you really need to understand the context.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/career/2014/10/01/hello-sdl.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 17:15:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/career/2014/10/01/hello-sdl.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/sdl.jpg" alt="Hello SDL" title="Hello SDL" class="img-responsive"></p>

<p class="dropcap">I now have two weeks since I joined SDL as a <i>Language Platform Evangelist Developer</i>. Almost everyone asked me what does that mean and what will I do so I decided that I better explain here in detail. If you are looking for a general definition of the position you can find one on wikipedia but it won't help you too much. In order to understand it better you really need to understand the context.</p>

<h3>Who is SDL?</h3>

<p>First off all let me tell you a few words about SDL and what is the company doing. It started as language translation service company and quickly become also a company providing software for language translation. For many years this was the only domain where SDL activated but new interesting opportunities arise and the company made new acquisitions on domains like e-commerce, social media monitoring, web content management, analytics and so on. All this new products allowed SDL to re-position itself recently as a <a href="http://www.sdl.com/solutions/business-need/global-customer-experience-management/">global customer experience management</a> company. If you are looking for more details please have a look <a href="http://www.sdl.com/aboutus/aboutsdl/history.html">here</a> for the history of the company and <a href="http://www.sdl.com/aboutus/aboutsdl/vision-mission.html">here</a> for the new vision and mission.</p>

<h3>What I&#39;m going to do at SDL?</h3>

<p>As I previously said SDL is offering now <a href="http://www.sdl.com/solutions/business-need/global-customer-experience-management/">global customer experience management</a> and as you might already think when you say global you immediately think of multiple languages, which means translation. </p>

<p>I&#39;m going to be closely involved in <a href="http://www.sdl.com/products/sdl-trados-studio/">SDL Trados Studio</a> and <a href="https://languagecloud.sdl.com/">Language Cloud</a> and probably some other products depending on the needs. Most of my work will be around creating and growing the development community for this products, but I will also offer support and consultancy to clients and help the sale process when is necessary. Growing the development community can mean many things but here are some of they key things I will do:</p>

<ol>
<li>Explain better the current Studio API&#39;s and in what product areas it can be used.</li>
<li>Improve and simplify the current API based on community and clients feedback.</li>
<li>Contribute to the new Language Cloud SDK.</li>
<li>Simplify how we can use develop against the API&#39;s. The most important bit will be to have them open to all possible developers.</li>
<li>Speak at developer conferences and discuss about the API&#39;s and SDK&#39;s. If you have any suggestion or you want me at a conference just leave a comment.</li>
<li>Contribute and help develop the new community platform which we will launch in the near future.</li>
<li>Develop plugins based on customer needs. This will also act as examples for other developers.</li>
</ol>

<p>I think this is very interesting and I&#39;m really keen to see how things will evolve since there are many other things that I would like to do as part of my new role. Also SDL has some interesting plans around the community so stay tuned.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2014-10-01T17:15:00+03:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <dc:date>2015-05-05T22:20:00+03:00</dc:date>
  </channel>
</rss>