<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd"
  xmlns:trackback="http://madskills.com/public/xml/rss/module/trackback/">
  <channel>
    <title>Romulus Crisan</title>
    <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com</link>
    <description>Romulus Crisan is a software developer, trainer, speaker, agile.</description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2016 12:54:21 +0000</pubDate>
    <item>
      <title>About SDL Studio SDK</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2016/01/30/2016-01-30-age-of-developers-about-sdl-studio-sdk.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[I love small and simple things that help me be more productive with my work. This is the main reasons why some time ago I started to work on GroupShareKit and I&amp;amp;#x27;m now happy to say that this is now available for everyone to use it as they like. Not only that you can use it but is completely open source.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2016/01/30/2016-01-30-age-of-developers-about-sdl-studio-sdk.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2016 12:54:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2016/01/30/2016-01-30-age-of-developers-about-sdl-studio-sdk.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/about-sdl-studio-sdk.jpg" alt="about-sdl-studio-sdk.jpg" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">This is the 5th part of the <a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html" target="_blank">OpenExchange: Age of Developers</a> series. In the previous articles I talked about how to configure your development environment and also gave  some suggestion on how you can start the development for OpenExchange store. One of the steps from the development environment setup was to install the SDL Studio SDK and I think it's worth talking about it in a bit more detail.</p>

<h3 id="age-of-developers---table-of-contents">Age of developers - table of contents</h3>

<p>As I release parts of this series I will update this page with links to the articles.</p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-translator-code.html">I’m a translator do I need to write code?</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/05/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-developer-translation-industry.html">I’m a developer, why bother with translation industry?</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/25/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-build-environment.html">Configure OpenExchange development environment</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/10/09/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-where-do-i-start.html">OpenExchange:Where do I start?</a></li>
  <li>About SDL Studio SDK</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="what-is-an-sdk">What is an SDK?</h3>

<p>SDK stands for <strong>software development kit</strong> and typically is a set of software development tools that enable the creation of applications for certain software applications. What exactly an SDK contains differ between each target software applications. Sometimes it can be a set of libraries in certain programing languages, like <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/net">Microsoft .Net</a> or <a href="https://www.java.com">Java</a>, or it can contain a bunch of supporting tools. Typically the SDK cames as separate download since not every user might be interested in using this type of capabilities.If you are interested in more details you can have a look <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_development_kit">here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="what-can-i-find-the-sdl-studio-sdk">What can I find the SDL Studio SDK</h3>

<p>SDL Studio SDK comes as a separate download from the standard SDL Studio application. You can get it from the developer page located <a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/developer/sdk.html">here</a>. Here’s the list of things that will be installed with the SDK:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Sample applications, developed in C#, to demonstrate the basic capabilities of SDL Studio API’s. This applications are really for good to get started with one of the API’s but please bare in mind that they don’t cover the entire API’s so please also look for features in the <a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/developer/sdk.html">documention</a> or ask on our <a href="https://community.sdl.com/developers/language-developers/">developer community</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Microsoft Visual Studio project templates.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/introducing-groupsharekit/manage-nuget.png" alt="Manage Nuget" title="Manage Nuget" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<h3 id="documentation">Documentation</h3>

<p>For more details please have a look <a href="https://github.com/sdl/groupsharekit.net#groupsharekit---groupshare-rest-api-client-library-for-net-">here</a>. If you don’t find an answer don’t hesitate to ask a question on <a href="https://community.sdl.com/developers/language-developers/">language developer community</a>.</p>

<h3 id="contribution">Contribution</h3>

<p>GroupShareKit is open source and published under <a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT">MIT License</a> so if you would like to add a new feature or you find a bug please don’t hesitate to use the <a href="">issue tracker</a>. Of course you can do more than that by actually implementing the feature or the fix your looking for. Also you might find issues that are already opened with which you might be able to help. More about that <a href="https://github.com/sdl/groupsharekit.net/issues">here</a>.</p>

<p>If you wonder why should you contribute to open source projects read this <a href="http://opensource.about.com/od/what-is-open-source/fl/Why-Do-People-Contribute-to-Open-Source-Projects.htm">article</a>.</p>

<h3 id="happy-coding">Happy coding</h3>

<p>I’m really keen to hear about your experience with the library and what kind of integration you’ve done.</p>

<p>Please let me know if you have any comments or questions.</p>

<p><em>Picture: <a href="https://flic.kr/p/Q4MPv">kballo - SDK Bayonne</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2016-01-30T12:54:21+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introducing GroupShareKit</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl-groupshare/2015/11/15/introducing-groupsharekit.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[I love small and simple things that help me be more productive with my work. This is the main reasons why some time ago I started to work on GroupShareKit and I'm now happy to say that this is now available for everyone to use it as they like. Not only that you can use it but is completely open source.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl-groupshare/2015/11/15/introducing-groupsharekit.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2015 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl-groupshare/2015/11/15/introducing-groupsharekit.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/introducing-groupsharekit/introducing-groupsharekit.jpg" alt="Setting up build automation" title="Setting up build automation" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">I love small and simple things that help me be more productive with my work. This is the main reasons why some time ago I started to work on <a href="https://github.com/sdl/groupsharekit.net" target="_blank">GroupShareKit</a> and I'm now happy to say that this is now available for everyone to use it as they like. Not only that you can use it but is completely open source.</p>

<h3 id="what-is-groupsharekit">What is GroupShareKit?</h3>

<p>GroupShareKit is a client library targeting .NET 4.5 and above that provides an easy way to interact with <a href="http://sdldevelopmentpartners.sdlproducts.com/documentation/api">GroupShare Rest API</a>. This library will greatly simplify and reduce the work a developer has to do in order to consume resources available in GroupShare by reducing the amount of boilerplate code and configuration that has to be written. This way the developer can focus his time and work on the actual implementation that has to be done.</p>

<p>Another benefit of this library is that you don’t have to actually understand how rest API’s are working since all this will be completely hidden. If you are not sure what an rest API is please have a look <a href="http://schoolofdata.org/2013/11/18/web-apis-for-non-programmers/">here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="how-do-i-start">How do I start?</h3>

<p>Using GroupShareKit library is very simple and it doesn’t require to run any installer, all you have to do is a few clicks inside Microsoft Visual Studio. The first step you need to do is to open the project where you want to use GroupShareKit in Visual Studio. After the project is opened go in the <code>Solution Explorer</code> area (if you can’t find it just press CTRL+ALT+L inside Visual Studio), then right click on the project <code>References</code> and select <code>Manage Nuget packages...</code>(if you can’t see this option have a look <a href="https://docs.nuget.org/consume/installing-nuget">here</a>). This action will open a window where you need to search for <code>GroupShareKit</code> and once you get the result just click the install button. That’s all, you can start use the GroupShareKit library in your project.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/introducing-groupsharekit/manage-nuget.png" alt="Manage Nuget" title="Manage Nuget" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<h3 id="documentation">Documentation</h3>

<p>For more details please have a look <a href="https://github.com/sdl/groupsharekit.net#groupsharekit---groupshare-rest-api-client-library-for-net-">here</a>. If you don’t find an answer don’t hesitate to ask a question on <a href="https://community.sdl.com/developers/language-developers/">language developer community</a>.</p>

<h3 id="contribution">Contribution</h3>

<p>GroupShareKit is open source and published under <a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT">MIT License</a> so if you would like to add a new feature or you find a bug please don’t hesitate to use the <a href="">issue tracker</a>. Of course you can do more than that by actually implementing the feature or the fix your looking for. Also you might find issues that are already opened with which you might be able to help. More about that <a href="https://github.com/sdl/groupsharekit.net/issues">here</a>.</p>

<p>If you wonder why should you contribute to open source projects read this <a href="http://opensource.about.com/od/what-is-open-source/fl/Why-Do-People-Contribute-to-Open-Source-Projects.htm">article</a>.</p>

<h3 id="happy-coding">Happy coding</h3>

<p>I’m really keen to hear about your experience with the library and what kind of integration you’ve done.</p>

<p>Please let me know if you have any comments or questions.</p>

<p><em>Picture: <a href="https://flic.kr/p/5o9EuF">BOB008 - Swiss Army Knife</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-11-15T22:00:00+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Setting up build automation for .Net open source projects</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/opensource/2015/11/14/setting-up-build-automation-for-net-open-source-projects.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[GroupShare is a collaboration platform for translation teams that is helping streamline translation processes, reduce coordination efforts and offer a secure access to all in-house and external resources. I'm not going to get into details about GroupShare but if you want to know more have a look here. Since GroupShare is a collaboration platform it implies that there are ways to create and manage users. Out of the box GroupShare allows 2 types of users to be defined. One is the SDL type for which the username and password is created and stored in the GroupShare database. The second one is Windows type which means that the password is not stored in GroupShare database rather the user will be authenticated against a corporate network that is using Microsoft Active Directory service domain identity or other Windows accounts. While this is good enough in most of the situations there are customers that already have a system where they store users and would like to use that instead of having different users in various systems. To overcome this need GroupShare allows implementation of custom authentication providers.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/opensource/2015/11/14/setting-up-build-automation-for-net-open-source-projects.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2015 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/opensource/2015/11/14/setting-up-build-automation-for-net-open-source-projects.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/setting-up-build-automation-net-projects/setting-up-build.jpg" alt="Setting up build automation" title="Setting up build automation" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">In the last weeks I worked on a .net client library for <a href="http://www.sdl.com/cxc/language/translation-productivity/studio-groupshare/" target="_blank">SDL Studio GroupShare</a>. This new client library is open source and meant to simplify developers work in terms of consuming resources available in GroupShare, but more about this on a future article. As I was coming closer to make a new release of this library I was thinking that it would make perfect sense to automate the build. There are many reasons to do that but for me the most important one was to have a painless mechanism to verify contribution from other developers. I've setup build automation for a few projects but this was my first attempt to do it for an open source project. While the automation concepts are exactly the same as for any other project the tooling involved is a bit different, especially if you are coming from a Microsoft world.</p>

<h3 id="cloud-hosted-building-automation-for-net">Cloud hosted building automation for .NET</h3>

<p>Open source means that your entire source code is publicly available to everyone interested, if it’s not then what’s the point of having it open source? Being public it probably means that you are hosting your code in places like <a href="https://github.com/">Github</a>, honestly nowadays this is probably your best choice. My choice to host the code for the GroupShare client library was <a href="https://github.com/sdl/groupsharekit.net">Github</a> and based on my previous experience my first idea to setup build automation was to prepare a server somewhere that would be able to grab my code and run the build script. While I could have setup a server pretty easy I immediately step backed since I was having the feeling that this approach doesn’t fit the purpose, somehow this doesn’t fit on the open source world. The reason I was having this feeling is because somebody (me) had to invest time, effort and some money to keep the server run. Also there was no simple option to share this with the other developers interested in using or contributing to the library. So I started doing some research and I found out there are a bunch of cloud hosted services that provide build automation and each of them was integrating nicely with Github. The list is pretty long so I’ll share just a few that I found most interesting and popular among other developers: <a href="https://travis-ci.org/">Travis CI</a>, <a href="https://codeship.com/">Codeship</a> and <a href="https://drone.io/">Drone.io</a>. Awesome, just that none of them had support for Windows environments and my library was .net and I was not using either <a href="http://www.mono-project.com/">Mono</a> or <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/dotnet/archive/2014/12/04/introducing-net-core.aspx">.Net core</a>. So in my mind I was thinking that I should turn my attention to what Microsoft has to offer in terms of build automation since I’m pretty sure they’ll support Windows environments. I knew Microsoft had TFS Build as part of their on-premise enterprise solution and I also knew about their relatively new <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/products/what-is-visual-studio-online-vs.aspx">visual studio online</a> offering which should include also build automation. <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/products/what-is-visual-studio-online-vs.aspx">Visual studio online</a>  does offer this capability and can also be configured to grab the code from github, more about his <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/Library/vs/alm/Build/github/index?f=255&amp;MSPPError=-2147217396">here</a>. Awesome again, just that this feature is not completely free and unfortunately the pricing model is not simple and friendly to understand. So again I had to continue looking for other options and I finally found <a href="http://www.appveyor.com/">AppVeyor</a> which is completely free for open source projects and it’s supporting Windows environments, actually they market themselves as <code>... Continuous Integration and Deployment tools to every .NET developer ...</code>. It’s pretty obviously that my choice was <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/products/what-is-visual-studio-online-vs.aspx">Visual studio online</a> because … errr not. I choose <a href="http://www.appveyor.com/">AppVeyor</a> because of obvious reasons, but it’s a shame that Microsoft doesn’t have a simple free offering for open source projects given the recent strong movement towards open source.</p>

<h3 id="build-scripting">Build scripting</h3>

<p>At this point I had my source code on <a href="https://github.com/">Github</a> and choose <a href="http://www.appveyor.com/">AppVeyor</a> to run my builds. Linking them together was easy since <a href="http://www.appveyor.com/">AppVeyor</a> allows you to log in with your <a href="https://github.com/">Github</a> credentials and once you authorize <a href="http://www.appveyor.com/">AppVeyor</a> it’s just a matter of choosing the repository for which you want to build. At this point I highly recommend looking to the <a href="http://www.appveyor.com/docs">AppVeyor documentation</a> if you are not familiar with the platform.</p>

<p>After the linking was done <a href="http://www.appveyor.com/">AppVeyor</a> requires that you repository to have <code>appveyor.yml</code> file from which you can configure which build environment, deploy mechanism and build scripts to run. Since in my case the requirements where simple I pretty much left the default configuration. I only specified my build script:</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/03a1ba3d5cf4531f0152.js"></script>

<p>As you can see from my above script I basically run my cmd <a href="https://www.google.ro/search?sourceid=chrome-psyapi2&amp;ion=1&amp;espv=2&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;q=cmd%20script&amp;oq=cmd%20scri&amp;aqs=chrome.0.0j69i57j0l4.3162j0j7">Windows batch script</a> specifying two different targets one for building my library and one for run a few integration tests. The batch script is a bit more complicated at the first look but is really simple actually. The first step is to use <a href="https://www.nuget.org/">Nuget</a> to install to additional libraries that I need to run the build. First is <a href="http://fsharp.github.io/FAKE/">Fake</a>, more about this in a bit, and the XUnit test runner console that I need to run my integration tests since I’m using XUnit for testing instead of MS Tests.</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/02318ab4b34c76d19cdb.js"></script>

<p>Creating build automation script is not something that the .Net developer has to do and this is because the wonderful job done for him by Visual Studio. That is slowly changing because of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_integration">CI</a> practice. To build a .net project/solution you need run <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms171452.aspx">msbuild</a> (this is what Visual Studio does behind the scenes). MSBuild is extensible and you can alter the build process based on your need but the syntax is pretty complicated and verbose (completely written in xml), personally I don’t necessarily like it. Apparently I was not the only who didn’t like working directly with msbuild so the community created libraries to simplify the build process. This type of libraries are using a domain specific language based on a well know programming, like <a href="http://rake.rubyforge.org/">rake</a> using ruby or <a href="http://gruntjs.com/">grunt</a>/<a href="http://gulpjs.com/">gulp</a> using java-script. Any of this libraries can be used to create a .net build script since they have dedicated plugins from msbuild but you’ll have to add a new dependency on your build system. For rake you will have to install ruby and for grunt/gulp you will need <a href="https://nodejs.org/en/">nodejs</a>. Based on the same concept I found 2 other libraries based on .Net programming language which didn’t require additional dependencies. One is named <a href="http://fsharp.github.io/FAKE/">fake</a> using F# and <a href="https://github.com/sakeproject/sake">sake</a> using C#. Initially I was tempted to use sake because I feel much comfortable writing in C# and I’ve seen it’s used by Microsoft in their open source repositories but it’s not well documented so I decided to use fake. I’m not an F# developer so the syntax seems kind of weird to me but it doesn’t matter that much since you only need some basics and you can of course copy from other examples. For the GroupShare client library I ended up with this:</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/57efc7eee344e84cdb8c.js"></script>

<p>Looks a bit scary at first but just walk through it line by line and it will start make sense, especially if you’ve done some work with msbuild. First 23 lines are just setting a bunch of values and then defining some msbuild targets using fake dsl language. Name of the targets are meaningful for what they are doing.</p>

<h3 id="handling-sensitive-data">Handling sensitive data</h3>

<p>In an open source project all your information has to be public including your configuration settings, like api keys, user name or passwords. For example your application might use a mailing platform like <a href="http://www.mailgun.com/">mailigun</a> for which you have your own account which you don’t want to be shared with everyone. In a private project you don’t need to worry to much about this because typically this type of information end up in configuration file that can be accessed only by authorized people. Also you might run some integration tests as part of your build for which you might need some api key’s or credentials. The solution I found for handling sensitive data is to use <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Environment_variable">environment variables</a>. This are easy to configure on your machine, testing machine(s) and all of the build platforms allow configuring environment variables from and administrative panel.</p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>I hope this will give you a much clearer picture about options you have in terms of cloud hosted build platforms you can use for your project, especially open source. One thing I have to mention that each of the build platforms have offerings for non open source projects but for those you’ll have to pay.</p>

<p>Please let me know if you have any comments or questions.</p>

<p><em>Picture: <a href="https://flic.kr/p/oYw4LG">Wei-Feng Xue - Night wheel long exposure</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-11-14T18:00:00+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GroupShare custom authentication provider</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl-groupshare/2015/10/29/GroupShare-custom-authentication-provider.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[GroupShare is a collaboration platform for translation teams that is helping streamline translation processes, reduce coordination efforts and offer a secure access to all in-house and external resources. I'm not going to get into details about GroupShare but if you want to know more have a look here. Since GroupShare is a collaboration platform it implies that there are ways to create and manage users. Out of the box GroupShare allows 2 types of users to be defined. One is the SDL type for which the username and password is created and stored in the GroupShare database. The second one is Windows type which means that the password is not stored in GroupShare database rather the user will be authenticated against a corporate network that is using Microsoft Active Directory service domain identity or other Windows accounts. While this is good enough in most of the situations there are customers that already have a system where they store users and would like to use that instead of having different users in various systems. To overcome this need GroupShare allows implementation of custom authentication providers.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl-groupshare/2015/10/29/GroupShare-custom-authentication-provider.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2015 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl-groupshare/2015/10/29/GroupShare-custom-authentication-provider.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/groupshare-custom-authentication-provider/groupshare-custom-authentication-provider.png" alt="GroupShare custom authentication provider" title="GroupShare custom authentication provider" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">GroupShare is a collaboration platform for translation teams that is helping streamline translation processes, reduce coordination efforts and offer a secure access to all in-house and external resources. I'm not going to get into details about GroupShare but if you want to know more have a look <a href="http://www.translationzone.com/products/sdl-studio-groupshare/" target="_blank">here</a>. Since GroupShare is a collaboration platform it implies that there are ways to create and manage users. Out of the box GroupShare allows 2 types of users to be defined. One is the SDL type for which the username and password is created and stored in the GroupShare database. The second one is Windows type which means that the password is not stored in GroupShare database rather the user will be authenticated against a corporate network that is using Microsoft Active Directory service domain identity or other Windows accounts. While this is good enough in most of the situations there are customers that already have a system where they store users and would like to use that instead of having different users in various systems. To overcome this need GroupShare allows implementation of custom authentication providers.</p>

<h3 id="custom-authentication-provider">Custom authentication provider</h3>

<p>In order to implement a custom authentication provider you will have to implement a GroupShare plugin. Building such a plugin is very similar experience to building an SDL Studio plugin. Since GroupShare is built using Microsoft .NET you will have to use the Microsoft development platform and to be more specific for GroupShare 2015 you will need to use Microsoft .NET 4.5.2 version. The tool of choice for doing Microsoft .NET development is <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/">Visual Studio</a>. You can use any flavor of Visual Studio (including the <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/products/visual-studio-community-vs">free community edition</a>) but since you need to build your plugin for Microsoft .NET 4.5.2 you will have to use Visual Studio 2013 or later. Here are the steps you need to follow to create the plugin:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Using Visual Studio create a new project of type Class Library.</li>
  <li>
    <p>Add reference to the following assemblies (both can be found under <code>SDL Server\Application</code> folder of your GroupShare install location):</p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>Sdl.Core.PluginFramework.dll</p>

      <p>Sdl.StudioServer.Api.Core.dll</p>
    </blockquote>
  </li>
  <li>Add a new class to the project and name it accordingly to your needs.</li>
  <li>
    <p>Open the newly created class and decorate it with the attribute <code>CustomAuthenticationProviderExtention</code>. Also set attribute property <code>CanValidateUserExistance</code> to true.</p>

    <p><code>[CustomAuthenticationProviderExtention(CanValidateUserExistance = true)]</code></p>
  </li>
  <li>Inherit the newly created class from <code>ICustomAuthenticationProvider</code>. This will require to create 2 methods in your class <code>UserExists</code> and <code>ValidateCredentials</code>.</li>
  <li>Implemented this 2 new methods with your custom authentication logic.</li>
  <li>Add a new xml file to your project with the following naming format <code>{yourcustomname}.plugin.xml</code>. This is used to describe the plugin you are building and it will be used by GroupShare to load your plugin. The content of your file has to follow a certain structure. You can use the following example to build yours:</li>
</ol>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cromica/c8083af5d32caa6cdd63.js"></script>

<h3 id="signing">Signing</h3>

<p>Before you can deploy your plugin to GroupShare your plugin assembly must be signed. To sign it please send your plugin assembly to <code>app-signing@sdl.com</code>.</p>

<h3 id="deploy">Deploy</h3>

<p>To deploy your plugin you will have to copy the plugin.xml file described at point 7 to the <code>SDL Server\Application\Plugins</code> folder of your GroupShare install location. Next you need to drop your plugin assembly in the <code>SDL Server\Application</code> folder. If you have other dependencies to your plugin please copy those also to the <code>SDL Server\Application</code> folder.</p>

<h3 id="final-words">Final words</h3>

<p>You can find a complete sample implementation of a custom authentication provider <a href="https://github.com/sdl/Sdl-GroupShare-Custom-Authentication-Provider">here</a>.</p>

<p>Please let me know if you have any comments or questions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-10-29T19:00:00+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenExchange:Where do I start?</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/10/09/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-where-do-i-start.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[This is the 4th part of the OpenExchange: Age of Developers series and is meant to provide information about places you can use to learn the API's to build applications for OpenExchange store.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/10/09/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-where-do-i-start.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2015 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/10/09/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-where-do-i-start.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/age-of-developers-where-do-i-start/age-of-developers-where-do-i-start.jpg" alt="training day" title="training day" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">This is the 4th part of the <a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html" target="_blank">OpenExchange: Age of Developers</a> series and is meant to provide information about places you can use to learn the API's to build applications for OpenExchange store.</p>

<h3 id="age-of-developers---table-of-contents">Age of developers - table of contents</h3>

<p>As I release parts of this series I will update this page with links to the articles.</p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-translator-code.html">I’m a translator do I need to write code?</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/05/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-developer-translation-industry.html">I’m a developer, why bother with translation industry?</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/25/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-build-environment.html">Configure OpenExchange development environment</a></li>
  <li>OpenExchange:Where do I start?</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="learning-places">Learning places</h3>

<p>First of all please make sure you have the development environment configured. If you’re not sure have a look <a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/25/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-build-environment.html">here</a>. Now lets see the places from where you can get information and help:</p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/developer/sdk.html">Developer page</a> This is the place from where you can browse or download the API’s help. Have a look at the available API’s and based on your needs drill-down to details.
2.<a href="https://community.sdl.com/developers/language-developers/">Language developers community</a> As you go along with your work and experiments it’s inevitable that you’ll have questions and the best way to answer questions is by discussing them with other people. Some people might already faced the same issues, others can help based on their experience or maybe just see the problem from a different angle. Take advantage of the dedicated language developers community and ask your questions, don’t be afraid nobody will judge or bite.</li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html">Age of developers series</a> This blog series it’s about providing useful information to people looking to develop applications for OpenExchange.</li>
  <li><a href="http://producthelp.sdl.com/SDK/Installer/4.0/SDLTradosStudio2015SDK.exe?s=220754%7C20150929122123%7C0xc14fa61273cb403b6b17b8063f985709b69a88ee">SDK Samples</a> Downloading and installing the SDK is part of the development environment configuration. Besides project templates it also comes with sample projects that you can use for learning or starting a new project.</li>
  <li><a href="http://sdl.github.io/#language">Open Source projects</a> We’ve open sourced more than 10 applications which are published on OpenExchange. This way you can see real code that is in production today, used by translators, reviewers and project managers on a daily basis. You can see real solutions to real problems not just samples.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="final-words">Final words</h3>

<p>We’re working to provide more and more materials that help people get engage so please let us know if you have any suggestions and ideas about what kind of materials you consider it will help you.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-10-09T19:00:00+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Studio API Training Day</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/10/05/Studio%20API%20Training%20Day.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[By this time some of you are already aware of my Age of Developers initiative. This initiative is meant to help everyone which would like to build applications for OpenExchange store or integrate SDL language products in their organization. Another way to learn develop applications for OpenExchange store is by going to a training. Now I have to say this is not something that happens regularly but if there is enough demand it can be arranged. For example last month we had an opportunity for a one day Studio API training at the Saint-Petersburg State University Of Aerospace Instrumentation with students from their language and computer systems faculties. Let me talk a bit about what was covered in this one day training.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/10/05/Studio%20API%20Training%20Day.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/10/05/Studio%20API%20Training%20Day.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/studio-api-training-day/studio-api-training-day.jpg" alt="training day" title="training day" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">By this time some of you are already aware of my <a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html" target="_blank">Age of Developers</a> initiative. This initiative is meant to help everyone which would like to build applications for <a href="translationzone.com/openexchange/" target="_blank">OpenExchange store</a> or integrate SDL language products in their organization. Another way to learn develop applications for <a href="translationzone.com/openexchange/" target="_blank">OpenExchange store</a> is by going to a training. Now I have to say this is not something that happens regularly but if there is enough demand it can be arranged. For example last month we had an opportunity for a one day Studio API training at the <a href="http://suai.ru/" target="_blank">Saint-Petersburg State University Of Aerospace Instrumentation</a> with students from their language and computer systems faculties and I would like to briefly share with you what we covered.</p>

<h3 id="what-a-day">What a day</h3>

<p>As a personal opinion I see training’s as a jump-start and eye opener since nobody becomes an expert in one day. In order to become one it requires lots of work, perseverance and patience. Having that said the objective of this training was to familiarize the students with some translation industry concepts, like translation memories, and the Studio API. One really important aspect that I need to mention is that none of them had any previous contacts with the translation industry. Because of this our first part of the training day was focused on showing and explaining SDL Studio together with API. After this first part we had 3 coding sessions in which each of the participant worked on the same <a href="https://github.com/sdl/Sdl-Community/tree/master/Record%20Source%20TU">application</a> on his development machine. In two of the sessions they were following me as I was writing parts of the applications and in the third (last) session they worked in small teams of 3 people to try and implement the final bits.</p>

<div class="owl-carousel text-left" data-navigation="true" data-singleitem="true" data-autoplay="true" data-transition="fade">
	<div class="item dragCursor">
		<img src="/assets/images/posts/studio-api-training-day/1.jpg" class="img-responsive" alt="img" />
	</div>
	<div class="item dragCursor">
		<img src="/assets/images/posts/studio-api-training-day/2.jpg" class="img-responsive" alt="img" />
	</div>
	<div class="item dragCursor">
		<img src="/assets/images/posts/studio-api-training-day/3.jpg" class="img-responsive" alt="img" />
	</div>
	<div class="item dragCursor">
		<img src="/assets/images/posts/studio-api-training-day/4.jpg" class="img-responsive" alt="img" />
	</div>
	<div class="item dragCursor">
		<img src="/assets/images/posts/studio-api-training-day/5.jpg" class="img-responsive" alt="img" />
	</div>
</div>

<h3 id="saint-petersburg">Saint Petersburg</h3>

<p>Well this is not about the training but it was my first time in <a href="https://www.flickr.com/search/?text=saint%20petersburg">Saint-Petersburg</a> and Russia. It’s a really nice town which I highly recommend to visit if you have the chance. People are very nice and there are plenty of <a href="http://www.tripadvisor.com/Attractions-g298507-Activities-St_Petersburg_Northwestern_District.html">things to do</a>. I know I would like to have the chance to go again</p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>If you are interested in more details or have any questions please leave a comment.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-10-05T19:00:00+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Translate,Measure,Compete...#YourProductivity</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/27/Translate-Measure-Compete-YourProductivity.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[A few months back during a brainstorm session me an and Paul Filkin where playing with some ideas on how we could help translators improve their productivity. It was clear from the beginning that we need to provide some metrics that will help translators understand how they are performing but we also wanted to make it in a fun way. We ended with a few ideas which we then refined with sales and marketing teams from SDL and started the work. I'm happy to say that you can now see the results on OpenExchange as #YourProductivity application.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/27/Translate-Measure-Compete-YourProductivity.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2015 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/27/Translate-Measure-Compete-YourProductivity.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/yourproductivity/leaderboard.png" alt="Leaderboard" title="Leaderboard" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">A few months back during a brainstorm session me an and <a href="http://multifarious.filkin.com/" target="_blank">Paul Filkin</a> where playing with some ideas on how we could help translators improve their productivity. It was clear from the beginning that we need to provide some metrics that will help translators understand how they are performing but we also wanted to make it in a fun way. We ended with a few ideas which we then refined with sales and marketing teams from SDL and started the work. I'm happy to say that you can now see the results on OpenExchange as <a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/app/yourproductivity-861.html#88985" target="_blank">#YourProductivity</a> application.</p>

<h3 id="yourproductivity">#YourProductivity</h3>

<p>The #YourProductivity application has 2 main components. One is the SDL Studio plugin that you can get download from <a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/app/yourproductivity-861.html#88985">here</a>. Once the download is finished all you have to do is double click the file and follow the steps to install the plugin. The second component is a leaderboard  web application that can be access from <a href="http://www.translationzone.com/community/app/community-productivity/">here</a>. Now let me explain a bit each of this 2 components</p>

<h3 id="sdl-studio-plugin">SDL Studio plugin</h3>

<p>Once you install the plugin when you will go in the SDL Studio editor view you will see a new section in the ribbon, after the project settings, named #YourProductivity. There are 3 buttons available in this section:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Productivity score</strong> - this will open the productivity score window where you will be able to find all the information about your productivity.</li>
  <li><strong>Share</strong> - this will open a window which will allow you to share the score on the leaderboard and on twitter. In order to share your score you will need to configure your twitter account.</li>
  <li><strong>Leaderboard</strong> - this will open, in your default web browser, the leaderboard web application.</li>
</ol>

<p>As you probably realized the central point is the <em>productivity score</em> window where you will be able to find all the productivity metrics and the score you can share on the leaderboard to enter the competition. Yes you’ve heard  correctly there is also a competition and prizes bot more on that a bit later. A picture is worth a thousand words so have a look at the next screen shot and I will explain some of the elements you can find in that screen.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/yourproductivity/productivity-score.png" alt="Productivity Score" title="Productivity Score" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p>On the top left-hand side you can find your score that you can share on the leaderboard and if you configured your twitter account then you will also see the icon and your name. I want to point out the fact that you can use this app without configuring the twitter account but in this case you will not be able to share the score or see your twitter image and name. Also the only information that is shared on the leaderboard is the score on the left-hand side, all the other information is just for you, saved on the local machine, and is meant to help you understand how well you are taking advantage of the productivity features provided by SDL Studio. The <em>translation efficiency</em> percentage is the main indicator of that. You can also find a list of all the projects you’ve worked on, together with the files you’ve touched during the translation. For each file you can find information on how many characters where inserted during translation process,this includes characters from TM’s or AT, how many keystrokes you’ve used and how efficient you were on that specific file. You should aim to have the <em>keystrokes saved</em> number as high as possible.</p>

<h3 id="leaderboard">Leaderboard</h3>

<p>The leaderboard is a public web application, so you can have a look at it even if you haven’t shared anything on it. Based on the scores on the leaderboard at the end of each month the top 3 positions, along with 4 lucky users selected at random, will receive Amazon gift cards worth up to €150.</p>

<p>At the end of each month both the leaderboard and the information you find in the SDL Studio plugin will be cleared so if you didn’t get a chance in the competition this month you can definitely do it next month.</p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>This is the first release of the application, we already have some ideas for the next version but it would be great to get some feedback from you.</p>

<p>If you want to learn more about the app and how it was build you can find me in Amsterdam in the week starting with 14th of September for the <a href="https://community.sdl.com/products-solutions/language/translationproductivity/c/e/102?mkt_tok=3RkMMJWWfF9wsRonvq7KcO%2FhmjTEU5z17%2BgtWaCwhokz2EFye%2BLIHETpodcMT8JlNbzYDBceEJhqyQJxPr3DJNkN1tloRhTgDQ%3D%3D">SDL Open House</a> and <a href="https://community.sdl.com/events/sdl_community_open_sept_2015_amsterdam/c/e/65?mkt_tok=3RkMMJWWfF9wsRonvq7KcO%2FhmjTEU5z17%2BgtWaCwhokz2EFye%2BLIHETpodcMT8JlNbzYDBceEJhqyQJxPr3DJNkN1tloRhTgDQ%3D%3D">Hackathon</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-08-27T19:00:00+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Configure OpenExchange development environment</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/25/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-build-environment.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[This is the third part of the OpenExchange: Age of Developers series and is meant to provide guideline on how to setup the development environment for OpenExchange.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/25/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-build-environment.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2015 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/25/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-build-environment.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/age-of-developers-build-ox-environment/age-of-developers-build-ox-environment.jpg" alt="Age Of Developers" title="Age of Developers" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">This is the third part of the <a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html" target="_blank">OpenExchange: Age of Developers</a> series and is meant to provide guideline on how to setup the development environment for OpenExchange.</p>

<h3 id="age-of-developers---table-of-contents">Age of developers - table of contents</h3>

<p>As I release parts of this series I will update this page with links to the articles.</p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-translator-code.html">I’m a translator do I need to write code?</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/05/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-developer-translation-industry.html">I’m a developer, why bother with translation industry?</a></li>
  <li>Configure OpenExchange development environment</li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/10/09/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-where-do-i-start.html">OpenExchange:Where do I start?</a></li>
</ol>

<h3 id="first-things-first">First things first</h3>

<p>In my previous article I tried to articulate why developing applications or plugins for OpenExchange can bring you benefits regardless if you are a developer or not. Now it’s time to move on and start get our hands dirty. Before starting any development you need to prepare your machine/laptop and based on which Studio(2014 or 2015) version are you going to use the configuration might be a bit different but let’s take it step by step:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Operating system</strong> - Since the development is done using Microsoft .NET at least for the moment this is only possible only on Windows operating systems. The minimum version you should use is Windows Vista SP2 but I highly recommend to try and use Windows 7 or later. If you want to develop on Windows server that’s fine but you need to have at least Windows Server 2008 SP2.</li>
  <li><strong>SDL Product</strong> - At the moment you can build applications around a few SDL products like Multiterm, Passolo or Studio. Based on which plugin you want to build you will need a licensed product. Now if you don’t have a license don’t worry because if you register <a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/developer/">here</a> and join the SDL Developer Program we can help you with the licenses you need for development.</li>
  <li><strong>SDK</strong> - You can download the SDK for the product you’re looking to develop from <a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/developer/sdk.html">here</a>. Now before going forward I would like to clarify what exactly you get and what you don’t get with this SDK’s. The main purpose for the SDK’s is to help the developer in building the application and this why with the SDK you get some code samples, documentation, Microsoft Visual Studio project templates (2012, 2013 and soon 2015) and build targets that are used by Microsoft Visual Studio to create your <em>sdlplugin</em> file at each build. You won’t get the product API with the SDK since this is already part of the application.</li>
  <li><strong>Microsoft .Net</strong> - This depends on the SDL Studio version you are developing for. SDL Studio 2014 uses .Net framework 4.0.3 and SDL Studio 2015 uses .Net framewrok 4.5.2. Based on the operating system you might already have .net installed on your machine.</li>
  <li><strong>Microsoft Visual Studio</strong> - For SDL Studio 2014 development you can use any version of Visual Studio starting from Visual Studio 2010 and for SDL Studio 2015 you need to use Visual Studio 2013 or later. I highly recommend to use Visual Studio 2013 or 2015. For this 2 versions you can use the community edition which is completely free and offers the same features like the professional version. More details about it <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/products/visual-studio-community-vs.aspx">here</a>.</li>
</ol>

<p>There aren’t a lot of things to be installed and configured but it might take some time to install all of them.</p>

<h3 id="version-control">Version control</h3>

<p>A version control system allows you to track the changes you’ve done to a file or a set of files. It is also backing up your files on some server/cloud. A few people might say that this is not necessary for small projects because it’s an overhead. This might be true but there are plenty of other reasons to do it:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Files are backed up on a server/cloud and in case your machine crashes you don’t loose all your work.</li>
  <li>Every change you make to a file is tracked and version-ed. This means you can always rollback to a previous version if you’ve done something bad in your current version.</li>
  <li>What do you do if you have multiple development machines, like a desktop and a laptop? Synchronizing between them can give you lot’s of headaches.</li>
  <li>There are free solutions like <a href="https://github.com/">github</a> or <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/products/visual-studio-online-pricing-vs.aspx">visual studio online</a>. Now github is free for as many users as you like as long as your project is public (you should consider open source licensing in this case). Visual Studio online is free but only for the 5 users. I’m pretty sure that one of this options will fit your needs.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-08-25T10:00:00+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I'm a developer, why bother with translation industry?</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/05/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-developer-translation-industry.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[This is the second part of the OpenExchange: Age of Developers series and is meant to highlight a few benefits of getting involved in the translation industry as a developer.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/05/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-developer-translation-industry.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2015 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/05/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-developer-translation-industry.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/age-of-developers-developer-translation-industry/developer-translation-industry.jpg" alt="Age Of Developers" title="Age of Developers" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">This is the second part of the <a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html" target="_blank">OpenExchange: Age of Developers</a> series and is meant to highlight a few benefits of getting involved in the translation industry as a developer.</p>

<h3 id="age-of-developers---table-of-contents">Age of developers - table of contents</h3>

<p>As I release parts of this series I will update this page with links to the articles.</p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-translator-code.html">I’m a translator do I need to write code?</a></li>
  <li>I’m a developer, why bother with translation industry?</li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/25/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-build-environment.html">Configure OpenExchange development environment</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/10/09/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-where-do-i-start.html">OpenExchange:Where do I start?</a></li>
</ol>

<h3 id="translation-industry">Translation industry</h3>

<p>I’m a developer, my heart beats 01010101…, so I’m not going to bore you with market shares, revenues and other big numbers about how big this industry is. If you are really curious about this have a look <a href="http://www.pangeanic.com/knowledge_center/size-of-the-translation-industry/#">here</a>. What I would like to say is how important this industry is in today’s world and to sustain my affirmation look at these numbers:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Only 27% of Internet users speak English</li>
  <li>70% of internet traffic comes from non-English native countries</li>
  <li>34% of Twitter messages are in English</li>
  <li>75% of Facebook users are outside of US</li>
</ul>

<p>Interesting numbers I must say and they clearly show how relevant this industry is. Now some of you might have heard about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Machine_translation">machine translation</a> but the translation industry is much more than that. It’s about language localization, interpretation and terminology.</p>

<h3 id="technology">Technology</h3>

<p>Now let’s get closer to what we as developers are interested in, which is the technology. Each industry has its own specific terminology so I would like to take this opportunity to briefly explain some of the terms:</p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="http://www.translationzone.com/products/cat-tools/">CAT tools (Computer-Assisted Translation)</a> - typically these are desktop applications that aid translators and linguists to increase their translation productivity. While these applications will continue to be predominant on the desktop, web solutions will slowly appear that will add new options for translators and linguists.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.translationzone.com/products/translation-memory/#tag1">Translation Memories</a> - this are databases that store segments, which can be sentences, paragraphs, headings, titles or elements, from any filetype, in a list that has been translated. CAT tools rely on translation memories to aid the translator during the translation.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.translationzone.com/products/terminology-management/#tag1">Termbase</a> - this is a central repository, like a database, which allows translators to systematically manage approved terms.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.translationzone.com/products/machine-translation/#tag1">Machine translation</a> - this is about automated translation of natural languages. Probably all of you have used <a href="http://www.freetranslation.com/">free translation</a> or <a href="https://translate.google.ro/">google translate</a> which are the great examples of machine translation at work. The examples I’ve given are just end-user products but each platform exposes machine translation capabilities through various api’s as part of a <a href="https://languagecloud.sdl.com/translation-toolkit/api-documentation">cloud offering</a>.</li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Postediting">Post-editing</a> - this is the process of improving a machine generated translation and typically is done from a CAT tool.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="why-bother">Why bother?</h3>

<p>Now that I’ve given you a brief overview of the translation industry the big question is why should I, as a developer, bother getting into this. I already know desktop, web, mobile and/or cloud technologies and I also have to keep up with the fast pace of technology changes. That might be true but if you really want to be a great specialist it’s not enough just to know some technologies, you need to make them relevant. People expect solutions for their problems from developers and good solutions require industry expertise. If someone asks you to build them an accounting system you don’t need to be an expert accountant but you need to know a few things about accounting. I highly recommend reading the article from John Sonmez “<a href="http://simpleprogrammer.com/2015/04/23/im-not-sure-i-want-to-be-a-specialist/">I’m not sure I want to be a specialist</a>” which emphasizes on specializing as a developer.</p>

<p>Becoming a specialist will help you become a better professional, find interesting job opportunities or even become a freelance developer if this is something you’re looking for.</p>

<p>Specializing in a specific industry makes perfect sense and this why I consider that you as a developer should take into consideration the translation industry.</p>

<h3 id="where-do-i-start">Where do I start?</h3>

<p>A great way to learn about the translation industry is to start develop plugins and apps for existing products. The <a href="www.sdl.com/openexchange">SDL OpenExchange</a> app store is nice way to publish your work and maybe even earn some money. At the very best you will gain exposure as a developer to those translations companies looking for development expertise to help them integrate their own systems or gain some competitive advantage by asking you to implement some ideas of their own. To publish an app on SDL OpenExchange you need to become an SDL OpenExchange developer. This is a simple process you can follow from <a href="http://www.translationzone.com/openexchange/developer/">here</a>. You don’t need to worry about licenses since SDL can offer dedicated developer licenses:</p>

<ol>
  <li>CAT Tool - SDL’s CAT tool name is <a href="http://www.sdl.com/cxc/language/translation-productivity/trados-studio/">SDL Trados Studio 2015</a> and in order to develop anything on top if it you’ll need a license. In order to get a developer license please create an SDL OpenExchange developer account and then send an email to app-signing@sdl.com and this will be sorted out</li>
  <li>Machine Translation - SDL’s machine translation cloud solution is named <a href="https://languagecloud.sdl.com/">Language Cloud</a> and you can sign-up for a developer account <a href="https://languagecloud.sdl.com/translation-toolkit/sign-up">here</a>.</li>
</ol>

<p>Every new journey might be a bit bumpy in the beginning and you should not hesitate to ask for help. I recommend to register in the <a href="https://community.sdl.com/developers/language-developers/">language developer community</a> and ask for help there.</p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>My best advice is to have patience, practice as much as possible and don’t be afraid to ask. I’m sure the results will come sooner or later. Happy coding.</p>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-08-05T10:00:00+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I'm a translator do I need to write code?</title>
      <link>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-translator-code.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[This is the first part of the OpenExchange: Age of Developers series. This article is meant to be a short guide for translators who are willing to augment their productivity and ease their day to day work by writing plugins for Sdl Studio, but they don't know from where to start.]]></description>
      <comments>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-translator-code.html#disqus_thread</comments>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2015 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-translator-code.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/age-of-developers-translator-code/age-of-developers-translator-code.jpg" alt="Age Of Developers" title="Age of Developers" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p class="dropcap">This is the first part of the <a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html" target="_blank">OpenExchange: Age of Developers</a> series. This article is meant to be a short guide for translators who are willing to augment their productivity and ease their day to day work by writing plugins for SDL Studio, but they don't know from where to start.</p>

<h3 id="age-of-developers---table-of-contents">Age of developers - table of contents</h3>

<p>As I release parts of this series I will update this page with links to the articles.</p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/07/20/OpenExchange-age-of-developers.html">Introduction</a></li>
  <li>I’m a translator do I need to write code?</li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/05/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-developer-translation-industry.html">I’m a developer, why bother with translation industry?</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/08/25/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-build-environment.html">Configure OpenExchange development environment</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://romuluscrisan.com/sdl%20studio/2015/10/09/OpenExchange-age-of-developers-where-do-i-start.html">OpenExchange:Where do I start?</a></li>
</ol>

<h3 id="im-a-translator-do-i-need-to-write-code">I’m a translator do I need to write code?</h3>

<p>The short answer is yes. In order to make an SDL Studio plugin and publish it on the SDL OpenExchange you need to write code. SDL Studio is developed using Microsoft technology called <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/net">Microsoft .Net</a>. The platform allows you to build all kind of apps from desktop (like Studio) to web and mobile. <a href="http://www.hanselman.com/">Scott Hanselman</a>, principal program manager and community architect at Microsoft, estimates that there are <a href="http://www.quora.com/How-many-NET-developers-are-there">~8 million</a> .net developers out there. The <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/net">Microsoft .Net</a> platform has support for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_CLI_languages">many programming languages</a> but the most popular is C# (CSharp). I would recommend learning this language because you will be able to find many resources to help you in your learning journey.</p>

<h3 id="why-should-i-bother">Why should I bother?</h3>

<p>This is a tough one to answer since every person is different and there is no silver bullet answer. Something that resonates with one person might not resonate for someone else. So here’s my list of reasons that might help you answer this question:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Are you waiting for a feature to be added in the software? Take the responsibility into your own hands and fix it. You will feel accomplished after you’ve done it, you will gain recognition in the industry and why not even see if you can earn some extra money with it.</li>
  <li><a href="http://simpleprogrammer.com/2013/03/31/everyone-should-learn-to-program-but-not-everyone-should-be-a-programmer/">Everyone Should Learn To Program, But Not Everyone Should Be A Programmer</a> What if only writers could write and when you needed to write an email to your boss you had to ask the company writer do it? I agree that programming and writing are not the same thing but what I’m trying to say is that learning to program doesn’t necessarily mean you became a professional developer. There’s much more than just writing code to being a professional developer.</li>
  <li>Nowadays learning to write code is much easier than it was 5, 10 or 20 years ago. You have much better tooling and the languages are much more abstract, meaning you don’t need to know all the details of how the computer works in order to write a line of code.</li>
  <li>There is a strong movement for every child to learn how to program. This doesn’t mean everyone should become a developer but it’s the best way to promote <a href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/link/research-notebook-computational-thinking-what-and-why">computational thinking</a>. Computational thinking teaches you how to tackle large problems by breaking them down into smaller, more manageable problems.</li>
</ul>

<p>I hope this will help you understand why should you bother to learn to program (or write code).</p>

<h3 id="where-do-i-start">Where do I start?</h3>

<p>The first thing you need to start writing apps for the SDL OpenExchange is Microsoft Visual Studio. This is the tool of choice when writing code for the <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/net">Microsoft .Net</a> platform. The good news is that you can get a free version with all the features you need. This version is called the Visual Studio Community Edition and can be downloaded from <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/products/visual-studio-community-vs.aspx">here</a>. You can select the 2015 or 2013 version, both of them are suitable for creating SDL OpenExchange plugins. 2015 has only just been released and contains lots of new features for experienced developers.</p>

<p>The next step would be to start learning some basics of programming in C#. There are books you can read, but personally I like watching videos so here’s some courses you could look into:</p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="https://www.microsoftvirtualacademy.com/en-US/training-courses/c-fundamentals-for-absolute-beginners-8295">C# Fundamentals for Absolute Beginners</a> This will walk you through all the code examples you need to build basic applications using C#. At the time this video was recorded the Visual Studio Community Edition had not been released so this is not mentioned but I recommend you to use it instead of the Visual Studio Express Edition.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.microsoftvirtualacademy.com/en-US/training-courses/software-development-fundamentals-8248">Software Development Fundamentals</a> This is a very detailed presentation on software development in general not necessarily only with C#. Some of the parts might be a bit advanced and are not essential if the main objective here is to learn some basic programming rather than becoming a programmer.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.pluralsight.com/courses/csharp-fundamentals-csharp5">C# Fundamentals with C# 5.0</a> This is a great video which I highly recommend but it’s different to the first two in my list because you have to pay for this service. You do get over 4000 courses of great quality though!</li>
</ol>

<p>Although watching those videos provides lots of information the best way to really learn is by practice, so I highly suggest you stop the videos and practice what you’ve seen at every opportunity.</p>

<p>If you prefer to learn from books I highly recommend <a href="http://csharpindepth.com/">C# in depth</a> but I would still suggest you supplement the book with some of the above videos.</p>

<p>One last thing, you’re not alone in this so don’t hesitate to ask for help. As I’ve said earlier in the article, there’s a really big .net community. My suggestions would be to ask any questions on the <a href="https://community.sdl.com/developers/language-developers/">SDL Language Developers</a> community website. Don’t hesitate to ask general programming questions in there even if they are not directly related to any of SDL products. There is the <a href="https://community.sdl.com/developers/language-developers/f/61">Getting Started</a> area which is just the right place for this type of discussion.</p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>My best advice is to have patience, practice as much as possible and don’t be afraid to ask. I’m sure the results will come sooner or later. Happy coding.</p>

<p>Please leave a comment if you have any questions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-07-20T10:00:00+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <dc:date>2016-01-30T12:54:21+00:00</dc:date>
  </channel>
</rss>